<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Baldur's Gate 3 on Aestus Guides - Memoirs of a CRPG Sage</title><link>https://www.aestusguides.com/categories/baldurs-gate-3/</link><description>Recent content in Baldur's Gate 3 on Aestus Guides - Memoirs of a CRPG Sage</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.aestusguides.com/categories/baldurs-gate-3/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Baldur's Gate 3 Race Tier List Guide</title><link>https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/tier_list.png" alt="Featured image of post Baldur's Gate 3 Race Tier List Guide" />&lt;h1 id="guide-baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list">Guide Baldur&amp;rsquo;s Gate 3 Race Tier List
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>Here is my Baldur&amp;rsquo;s Gate 3 Race Tier List! If you&amp;rsquo;ve watched my &lt;a class="link" href="https://youtu.be/nqgcy5yV6V4" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Youtube video&lt;/a> on this subject, this article is the reference sheet for that. Any changes in my opinions will be reflected in this article, which is to say it represents my up to date opinion on race rankings. I hope you enjoy it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The basic principle for evaluating races is this: look for impactful features that you can’t easily get from other parts of a build. Take Darkvision for example. It is an useful feature, for sure, but its also so easy to get regardless of your race. You can check that box with the Light cantrip, the Darkvision spell, through Radiating Orb, or just through cheap consumables. By contrast Superior Darkvision is a different story! As far as I know, you can get it with the Devils Sight invocation and as a level 3 feature for Gloomstalkers only, so there are many builds that will want Superior Darkvision from their race selection.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Besides that, the other big thing to note is that attribute bonuses have now been standardized between all the race choices. Now all races will get a +2 to one attribute of their choice and a +1 to a different attribute of their choice. This is a big change compared to early access! Now, what makes a race good is their actual racial features, rather then their attribute bonuses.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With those things in mind, lets dive into the tier list!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="dwarf">Dwarf
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/gold_dwarf.png"
width="800"
height="367"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/gold_dwarf_hu_efe89058565544c2.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/gold_dwarf_hu_1655b276fcf113bc.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Gold Dwarf Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="217"
data-flex-basis="523px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="gold-dwarf---b-tier">Gold Dwarf - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Medium&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 7.5m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Darkvision.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dwarven Resilience. You have advantage on saving throws against being poisoned, and you have resistance against poison damage.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dwarven Combat Training. You have proficiency with the battleaxe, handaxe, light hammer, and warhammer.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dwarven Toughness. Your hit point maximum increases by 1, and it increases by 1 every time you gain a level.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Dwarven Resilience isn’t as impactful as you would expect it to be. In short, there are better, cheaper ways to get damage resistances, so the damage resistance part of the ability isn&amp;rsquo;t as attractive as it used to be. The advantage to the poison condition is useful, but not highly impactful on most runs. Dwarven Toughness, Combat Training, and Darkvision are all useful abilities that are also short of being highly impactful for any build. Altogether, its useful but not highly impactful on every class, which is the very definition of B-Tier for me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/shield_dwarf.png"
width="800"
height="369"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/shield_dwarf_hu_3a76a4390b0be519.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/shield_dwarf_hu_9e33e8ec2a0d94d3.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Shield Dwarf Protrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="216"
data-flex-basis="520px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="shield-dwarf---b-tier">Shield Dwarf - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Medium&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 7.5m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Darkvision.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dwarven Resilience. You have advantage on saving throws against being poisoned, and you have resistance against poison damage.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dwarven Combat Training. You have proficiency with the battleaxe, handaxe, light hammer, and warhammer.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dwarven Armor Training. You have proficiency with light and medium armor.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Shield Dwarf trades the +1 hit point per level – a bonus that is equally useful for all classes – for light and medium armor proficiency, a bonus that is better suited for caster classes. This makes Shield Dwarves the caster dwarf option and Gold Dwarf the martial dwarf option. While better for different classes, they both sit solidly in B-Tier for me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/duergar.png"
width="800"
height="368"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/duergar_hu_dfba17ebf23b6dba.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/duergar_hu_fb4031e3783e9c16.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Duergar Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="217"
data-flex-basis="521px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="duergar---s-tier">Duergar - S Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Medium&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 7.5m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Darkvision.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dwarven Resilience. You have advantage on saving throws against poison, and you have resistance against poison damage.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dwarven Combat Training. You have proficiency with the battleaxe, handaxe, light hammer, and warhammer.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Duergar Resilience.You have advantage on saving throws against illusions as well as against being charmed or paralyzed.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Duergar Magic. Starting at 3rd level, as an actio you can cast the Enlarge spell on yourself once per long rest.Starting at 5th level, you can also cast the Invisibility on yourself as an action once per battle. Outside of battle it is an infinite cast spell.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Kind of like a better version of Hill Dwarf in that what it gives is useful for literally every class. Duergar Resilience is amazing because of advantage against Paralyze saving throws, probably the most crippling status effect in the game. Both of its spell are consistently useful, too. The unique, once per battle casts version of invisibility is something I&amp;rsquo;ve explored quite a bit and here are some thoughts. Invisibility is a very useful spell for solving out of combat puzzles, like pickpocketing, avoiding difficult encounters, etc. In combat, its a way to drop aggro, get into an advantageous position, and reliably begin combats with surprise. Perfect for Assassin and/or Gloomstalker based builds but useful for practically every run. You just can’t go wrong picking this race.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/dragonborn_white.png"
width="800"
height="440"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/dragonborn_white_hu_7f807561b7c77f6c.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/dragonborn_white_hu_cdf138a6ef3f55f8.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="White Dragonborn Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="181"
data-flex-basis="436px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="dragonborn---c-tier">Dragonborn - C Tier
&lt;/h2>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Medium&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 9m.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Draconic Ancestry. You are distantly related to a particular kind of dragon. Choose a type of dragon from the below list; this determines the damage and area of your breath weapon, and the type of resistance you gain.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Black = Acid&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Blue = Lightning&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Green = Poison&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Red = Fire&lt;/li>
&lt;li>White = Cold&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Brass = Fire&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Bronze = Lightning&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Copper = Acid&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gold = Fire&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Silver = Cold&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Breath Weapon. When you use your breath weapon, all creatures in the area (probably 5m cone, maybe 1m by 9m line) must make a saving throw, the type of which is determined by your ancestry. The DC of this saving throw is 8 + your Constitution modifier + your proficiency bonus. After using your breath weapon, you cannot use it again until you complete a short rest. The damage increases b 1d6 at level 6 then again at level 11.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Damage Resistance. You have resistance to the damage type associated with your ancestry.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The damage on the breath weapon is so low that its practically never worth the action to use it. What we are left with then as far as desirable features go is just a damage resistance, but its so easy to get damage resistances in this game. Still, its something, so not RP Tier, but close.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/drow_seldarine.png"
width="800"
height="420"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/drow_seldarine_hu_7e222a8729782531.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/drow_seldarine_hu_62b3996883e98c11.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Seldarine Drow Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="190"
data-flex-basis="457px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="drow---a-tier">Drow - A Tier
&lt;/h2>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Medium&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 9m.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fey Ancestry. You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can&amp;rsquo;t put you to sleep.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Keen Senses. You have proficiency in the Perception skill.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Superior Darkvision.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Drow Magic. You know the Dancing Lights cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast the Faerie Fire spell once with this trait and regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest. When you reach 5th level, you can cast the Darkness spell once and regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for these spells.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Drow Weapon Training. You have proficiency with rapiers, shortswords, and hand crossbows.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Fey Ancestry is very good on any concentration class, especially early levels, since Sleep is the most reliable way enemies can break your concentration. Superior Darkvision is great for ranged attackers. The spell portfolio isn’t useless, but its not really good either. Keen Senses is just nice to have both in and out of combat. Put it altogether and Drow have a kit that is great for casters and ranged striker builds. Lots of useful things with this race.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="elf">Elf
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/high_elf.png"
width="800"
height="349"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/high_elf_hu_d4432634754a16ae.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/high_elf_hu_1645257db5025c3f.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="High Elf Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="229"
data-flex-basis="550px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="high-elf---b-tier">High Elf - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Medium&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 9m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Darkvision.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fey Ancestry. You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can&amp;rsquo;t put you to sleep.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Keen Senses. You have proficiency in the Perception skill.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Cantrip. You know one cantrip of your choice from the Wizard spell list. Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Elf Weapon Training. You have proficiency with the longsword, shortsword, shortbow, and longbow.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The unique thing that it gets compared to other elves is the intelligence cantrip which isn’t good enough for us to pick them in most cases. The cantrip is most useful on Eldritch Knight and Arcane Trickster builds, because they are intelligence based classes that don’t already have enough cantrips. Still, having Fey Ancestry and Keen Senses, and Elf Weapon Training is enough to keep them out of C-Tier.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/wood_elf.png"
width="800"
height="349"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/wood_elf_hu_ae76b3635401fc9.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/wood_elf_hu_ccf0dc589f70e116.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Wood Elf Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="229"
data-flex-basis="550px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="wood-elf---a-tier">Wood Elf - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Medium&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 10.5m (Fleet of Foot)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Darkvision.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fey Ancestry. You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can&amp;rsquo;t put you to sleep.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Keen Senses. You have proficiency in the Perception skill.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Elf Weapon Training. You have proficiency with the longsword, shortsword, shortbow, and longbow.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fleet of Foot. Your base walking speed increases to 10.5m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mask of the Wild. You have proficiency in the Stealth skill.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Just gets a lot of useful features that work for every class, including Fey Ancestry, Keen Senses, darkvision, and bonus movement for either closing distance or kiting. You can’t go wrong with wood elf. Both Stealth and Perception are useful skill proficiencies. Just a lot of minor useful things that add up to a versatile race.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/githyanki.png"
width="800"
height="453"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/githyanki_hu_27ac44ef1c27cab.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/githyanki_hu_e82e6958d84570d8.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Githyanki Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="176"
data-flex-basis="423px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="githyanki---a-tier">Githyanki - A Tier
&lt;/h2>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Medium&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 9m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Astral Knowledge: Gain proficiency in all skills corresponding to a chosen ability until your next long rest.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Martial Prodigy. You are proficient with light and medium armor and with shortswords, longswords, and greatswords.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Githyanki Psionics. You know the Mage Hand cantrip, and the hand is invisible when you cast the cantrip with this trait. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast the Jump spell once with this trait, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest. When you reach 5th level, you can cast the Misty Step spell once with this trait, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest. Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for these spells. When you cast them with this trait, they don&amp;rsquo;t require components.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>One feature that stands out is its weapon proficiencies, which include Greatswords, allowing you to go for a Great Weapon Master striker build on classes that don’t get martial weapon proficiency. Is that really worth doing? Not so much after level 5 when striker builds start needing more than just GWM but Extra Attack also, and every class that gets Extra Attack also gets martial weapon proficiency. I want to experiment more with it, but at this point I am doubtful there’s a high performing build that uses this strategy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Besides that, the spell portfolio is one of the best of any race. Medium armor proficiency is clutch for caster classes. Astral Knowledge is very fun and useful and adaptable in multiplayer games. Githyanki also get far and away the most unique items in the game. A very strong race overall!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="gnome">Gnome
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/forest_gnome.png"
width="800"
height="368"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/forest_gnome_hu_4d58112ce13ac04.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/forest_gnome_hu_936610c4795052aa.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Forest Gnome Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="217"
data-flex-basis="521px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="forest-gnome---rp-tier">Forest Gnome - RP Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Small&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 7.5&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Darkvision.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gnome Cunning. You have advantage on all Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saves against magic.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speak with Animals. Forest Gnomes can cast Speak with Animals once per long rest.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Both Forest Gnome and Rock Gnome get their most valuable feature just for being a Gnome. Their unique subrace features are extremely lackluster.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Gnome Cunning is incredible resilience that is useful for every build. Besides that Forest Gnomes just get darkvision to compensate for a -1 movement. Speak with Animals, so far, is an invaluable role play ability, since it opens up dozens of NPCs to interact with. However, you can talk to all the animals you want just by using Speak with Animal potions. Forest Gnome is the worst Gnome; there isn&amp;rsquo;t really a reason to pick it over the other Gnomes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/rock_gnome.png"
width="800"
height="368"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/rock_gnome_hu_c91a723081ef340d.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/rock_gnome_hu_79467304898ce5d4.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Rock Gnome Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="217"
data-flex-basis="521px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="rock-gnome---b-tier">Rock Gnome - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Small&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 7.5m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Darkvision.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gnome Cunning. You have advantage on all Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saves against magic.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Artificers Lore. Add twice your proficiency bonus to History checks.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The same as Forest Gnome, but trades expertise in history checks for Speak with Animals. History checks don’t offer much in terms of combat utility, either direct or indirect, but as a historian myself, I love the concept as a role play feature. These guys are one of my personal favorites.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/deep_gnome.png"
width="800"
height="368"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/deep_gnome_hu_67ef909b6752a2ce.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/deep_gnome_hu_f125670c1c658e71.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Deep Gnome Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="217"
data-flex-basis="521px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="deep-gnome---s-tier">Deep Gnome - S Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Small&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 7.5m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gnome Cunning. You have advantage on all Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saves against magic.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Superior Darkvision&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stone Camouflage. You have advantage on stealth checks.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In BG1 and 2, Gnomes were a power gamer’s dream, and my favorite race due to their tricksy, stealthy illusionist playstyle. Deep Gnome translates something like that into 5e, mixing superior darkvision and advantage on stealth checks to the already invaluable Gnome Cunning feature to cook up a surprisingly stacked kit. Stealth is the most valuable skill in the game in my opinion, and the Deep Gnome is the one of two races that get a feature that augments it beyond a simple proficiency. As we’ve discussed above, Superior Darkvision is good on everybody, but particularly good on ranged strikers/casters. This competes with Duergar as the GOAT for sneak and ranged striking builds.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="half-elf">Half-Elf
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/high_half_elf.png"
width="800"
height="387"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/high_half_elf_hu_4135d423f7c2ccb1.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/high_half_elf_hu_325f0b735732b363.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="High Half-Elf Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="206"
data-flex-basis="496px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="high-half-elf---b-tier">High Half-Elf - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Medium&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 9m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Civil Militia: You gain proficiency in all polearms, shields, and light armor&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Darkvision.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fey Ancestry. You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can&amp;rsquo;t put you to sleep.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Cantrip. You know one cantrip of your choice from the Wizard spell list. Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for it.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The big change here is civil militia – all Half-Elves get it – so let’s start with that. Shield and Light Armor proficiencies are excellent for caster classes, offering a big AC boost and an early game spike to concentration saves (through Spidersilk Armor + Safeguard Shield). Shields are really strong in BG3, so getting them on casters without needing to multi-class is valuable. The Polearm Proficiencies enable the Polearm Master fear for caster classes that otherwise are locked out from it. Is that worth doing on a caster? I’m not sure! It could be giving a front line caster something reliable to do with their bonus action and reaction. Then again, front line casters want their reaction for the Shield spell. Anyways, its interesting!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On top of that, the Half-Elf chassis gets darkvision and fey ancestry, decent features, but nothing special.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The High Half-Elf offers an intelligence-based wizard cantrip of your choice, which is both niche and negligible. See above in the High Elf entry.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/drow_half_elf.png"
width="800"
height="387"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/drow_half_elf_hu_4f3133d488f9ede1.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/drow_half_elf_hu_75ede8c05718131c.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Drow Half-Elf Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="206"
data-flex-basis="496px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="drow-half-elf---b-tier">Drow Half-Elf - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Medium&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 9m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Civil Militia: You gain proficiency in all polearms, shields, and light armor.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Darkvision.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fey Ancestry. You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can&amp;rsquo;t put you to sleep.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Drow Magic. You know the Dancing Lights cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast Faerie Fire once, and it recharges after a long rest. When you reach 5th level, you can cast Darkness once, and it recharges after a long rest. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for these spells.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>A Half-Elf chassis with added Drow Magic. Drow Magic is decent, but not great. While this race is slightly more versatile than the High Half-Elf, its not enough to bump it up a whole tier.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/wood_half_elf.png"
width="800"
height="387"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/wood_half_elf_hu_fc7c0386c72bd745.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/wood_half_elf_hu_e0d6a4046e657f90.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Wood Half-Elf Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="206"
data-flex-basis="496px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="wood-half-elf---a-tier">Wood Half-Elf - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Medium&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 10.5m (Fleet of Foot)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Civil Militia: You gain proficiency in all polearms, shields, and light armor.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Darkvision.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fey Ancestry. You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can&amp;rsquo;t put you to sleep.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fleet of Foot. your base speed is increased to 10.5m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mask of the Wild. You gain proficiency in stealth.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Adds +1 movement and a stealth proficiency to the Half-Elf foundation. As we’ve already discussed, those are useful features on practically every class, making Wood Half-Elf the variant of choice.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/half_orc.png"
width="800"
height="422"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/half_orc_hu_fbc86f0231e825a1.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/half_orc_hu_981db4c6efee421.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Half Orc Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="189"
data-flex-basis="454px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="half-orc---s-tier">Half Orc - S Tier
&lt;/h2>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Speed. 9m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Darkvision.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Menacing. You gain proficiency in the Intimidation skill.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Relentless Endurance. When you are reduced to 0 hit points but not killed outright, you can drop to 1 hit point instead. You can&amp;rsquo;t use this feature again until you finish a long rest.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Savage Attacks. When you score a critical hit with a melee weapon attack, you can roll one of the weapon&amp;rsquo;s damage dice one additional time and add it to the extra damage of the critical hit.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This race gets two very unique and powerful abilities that make it both versatile and the premier class for melee strikers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To start off with less good stuff, Darkvision is Darkvision, and proficiency in Intimidate is great out of combat utility. The social skills (Persuasion, Deception, and Intimidate) are always high value in terms of out-of-combat solutions to encounters, which can translate into genuine in-combat advantages that are hard to quantify.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now to the real good stuff! Relentless Endurace is like an automatic, free cast of Healing Word that can proc once per long rest. That is great on anybody but superb on melee characters who are most likely to go down at least once between rests.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Savage Attacks is more damage on crits. Its not a lot of extra damage, but it’s the only race feature that actually directly buffs your damage, probably because damage is just so important, getting it as a racial feature rockets that race to the top of the list.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Altogether Half-Orc is like the best mix of specialized race car with good-ole reliable Toyota sedan. It’s a high-performance pick for any and all strikers, but still offers useful features for everyone else too!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="halfling">Halfling
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/lightfoot_halfling.png"
width="800"
height="379"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/lightfoot_halfling_hu_baff1ed6c3e3077b.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/lightfoot_halfling_hu_ebbb0c3567a59e96.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Lightfoot Halfling Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="211"
data-flex-basis="506px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="lightfoot-halfling---s-tier">Lightfoot Halfling - S Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Small&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 7.5m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Lucky. When you roll a 1 on an attack roll, ability check, or saving throw, you can reroll the die. You must use the new result, even if it is a 1.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Brave. You have advantage on saving throws against being frightened.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Naturally Stealthy. You gain advantage in Stealth checks.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>We need to start by talking about Lucky. If you average it out across all possible outcomes Lucky translates to something like a +1 bonus, which is small, but even a small bonus that applies to all d20 rolls has a big impact since d20 rolls are the most common and the most impactful rolls in BG3. However, thinking of it just quantitatively misses a lot of what makes it so good. Qualitatively speaking, Lucky is a unique feature for mitigating RNG and offers a peace of mind that you just can’t get from anything else. With Lucky and a consistent source of advantage that pesky “1s always miss”rule dissolves into irrelevance and you can finally depend on ALWAYS hitting that attack or ALWAYs making that concentration save. Its hard to compare a feature like that to anything else. Judging Halflings is extremely hard for that reason and I find myself thinking about the choice between Halfling and other races as one of those genuine expressions of playstyle rather than a solvable, mathematical choice about optimization. I value it extremely highly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Of the two variations of Halfling though, Lightfoot is the lesser. It gives you advantage on stealth checks (see the entry for Deep Gnome above), which naturally inclines it towards stealth builds, but probably melee stealth builds, since it doesn’t get Superior Darkvision.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/strongheart_halfling.png"
width="800"
height="379"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/strongheart_halfling_hu_d671db27482b17c8.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/strongheart_halfling_hu_d829e38c1137b352.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Strongheart Halfling Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="211"
data-flex-basis="506px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="strongheart-halfling---s-tier">Strongheart Halfling - S Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Small&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 7.5m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Lucky. When you roll a 1 on an attack roll, ability check, or saving throw, you can reroll the die. You must use the new result, even if it is a 1.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Brave. You have advantage on saving throws against being frightened.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Strongheart Resilience. You have advantage on saving throws against being poisoned and resistance to poison damage.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Strongheart Halflings add Dwarven Resilience (renamed “Strongheart Resilience” but its mechanically the same) to the Halfling chassis. So, now you have a race that gives you advantage to saving throws against two very common status effects, resistance to one of the most common damage types, and Lucky (read Lightfoot Halfling entry above to understand how brilliant this feature is). Halflings are the master race!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/human.png"
width="800"
height="453"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/human_hu_32cd926264c58c86.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/human_hu_80729403f82d37a7.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Human Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="176"
data-flex-basis="423px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="human---rp-tier">Human - RP Tier
&lt;/h2>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Medium&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 9m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Civil Militia: You gain proficiency in all polearms, shields, and light armor&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Human Versatility: You gain proficiency in a skill of your choosing and your carrying capacity is increased by a quarter.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The big selling point here is Civil Militia, see the entry for High Half-Elf above for my discussion of it. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Human Versatility is kind of a meme, but increased carrying capacity is honestly such a good quality of life buff for me that I kind of like it. Technically, it has no combat utility, and the proficiency is nifty, but very unlikely to outweigh what, say, a High Wood-Elf offers. From an optimization perspective, you should always pick High Half-Elf over human, so RP-Tier.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="tiefling">Tiefling
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/asmodeus_tiefling.png"
width="800"
height="386"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/asmodeus_tiefling_hu_63a046f09fdcca5d.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/asmodeus_tiefling_hu_55c2fb71eaa471fc.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Asmodeus Tiefling Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="207"
data-flex-basis="497px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="asmodeus-tiefling---c-tier">Asmodeus Tiefling - C Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Medium.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 9m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Darkvision.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Resistance to Fire Damage&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Infernal Legacy. You know the Thaumaturgy cantrip. Once you reach 3rd level, you can cast the Hellish Rebuke spell once as a 2nd-level spell. Once you reach 5th level, you can also cast the Darkness spell once. You must finish a long rest to cast these spells again with this trait. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for these spells.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>All Tieflings give you Darkvision, resistance to fire damage, and an portfolio of spells. The spells vary by subrace. For A. Tieflings you get Thaumaturgy, Hellish Rebuke, and Darkness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Fire damage is a very common damage type, but its also a very common resistance. There are lots of other ways to get it, including the 2nd level Cleric spell Warding Bond, which you want to be casting anyways.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That leaves of with the spells. The A.Tiefling’s selection are all useful, but not unique enough to carve out a genuine niche for it as a choice.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/mephistopheles_tiefling.png"
width="800"
height="386"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/mephistopheles_tiefling_hu_f6584a4c08110cc7.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/mephistopheles_tiefling_hu_3527de0729c666e9.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Mephistopheles Tiefling Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="207"
data-flex-basis="497px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="mephistopheles-tiefling---c-tier">Mephistopheles Tiefling - C Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Medium.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 9m&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Resistance to Fire Damage.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Darkvision.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Legacy of Cania. You know the Mage Hand cantrip. Once you reach 3rd level, you can cast the Burning Hands spell once as a 2nd-level spell. Once you reach 5th level, you can also cast the Flame Blade spell once as a 3rd-level spell. You must finish a long rest to cast these spells again with this trait. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for these spells.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Mephistopheles Tiefling’s can cast Flame Blade after level 5, and that used to give them a niche. However, changes on full release have really put a dent in the Flame Blade strategy. Its no longer a concentration spell, but it only lasts 10 turns and its summoned to your main hand. More importantly, it no longer procs Circlet of Fire (now called Pyroquickness Hat). Still better than Asmodeus Tiefling.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/zariel_tiefling.png"
width="800"
height="386"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/zariel_tiefling_hu_408b356d4ee8d0d4.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/zariel_tiefling_hu_263c5a010a5cf7f8.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Zariel Tiefling Portrait"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="207"
data-flex-basis="497px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="zariel-tiefling---c-tier">Zariel Tiefling - C Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Size. Medium.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Speed. 9m.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Resistance to Fire Damage.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Darkvision.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Legacy of Avernus. You know the Thaumaturgy cantrip. Once you reach 3rd level, you can cast the Searing Smite spell once as a 2nd-level spell. Once you reach 5th level, you can also cast the Branding Smite spell once as a 3rd-level spell. You must finish a long rest to cast these spells again with this trait. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for these spells.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Zariel Tiefling’s spells augment your weapon attacks, so its intended to be for weapon based strikers, but for that person it is completely out muscled by Half-Orc. However, Branding Smite can be a encounter deciding spell, making this the best of the Tieflings in my opinion. It right on the edge of C and B Tier to me.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="summary">Summary
&lt;/h2>&lt;hr>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/tier_list.png"
width="1140"
height="465"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/tier_list_hu_b7d9435fd00016e4.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-race-tier-list/tier_list_hu_647580ed1a7ebf89.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Aestus BG3 Class TierList"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="245"
data-flex-basis="588px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="video">Video
&lt;/h2>&lt;div class="video-wrapper">
&lt;iframe loading="lazy"
src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/NZcT-Oo_d_4"
allowfullscreen
title="YouTube Video"
>
&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles" >Return home&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Fundamental Math in D&amp;D 5e and Baldur's Gate 3</title><link>https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/5e-bg3-fundamental-math/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/5e-bg3-fundamental-math/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/689ddf7723353a59fce740dea32c231b4a275d21-2360x1640.png?w=600&amp;fm=webp" alt="Featured image of post Fundamental Math in D&amp;D 5e and Baldur's Gate 3" />&lt;h1 id="guide-some-fundemental-math-in-5e-and-bg3">Guide Some Fundemental Math in 5e and BG3
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>This is a resource outlining what I consider the most important math for understanding D&amp;amp;D 5e and BG3. In it I detail important formulas you can use to calculate the power of your own builds, but I also explain as clearly as I can how we arrive at those formulas so that you can understand how it works, not just that it works. At the end I explore the math of power scaling – the so-called “flattened math” of 5e – with concrete examples and discuss how all of it should impact how we evaluate the relative strength of build choices.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My plan is to eventually write a similar one of these for Pathfinder, Pillars of Eternity, and the original Baldur’s Gate games as well so we can compare the fundamental math between all of the systems and see how they change what is strong in each system. They will be part of my &amp;ldquo;niche articles for hardcore fans&amp;rdquo; series for my patrons. If you like this article, consider subscribing to my &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.patreon.com/user?u=52365991&amp;amp;fan_landing=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Patreon&lt;/a> for more! I already have one article in the series that mathematically models the value of winning initiative.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="check-bonus-math">Check-Bonus Math
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>The core method of arbitrating success in D&amp;amp;D 5e and BG3 is the D20 roll. All the really important D20 roles follow the same pattern, which I call the “Check-Bonus” pattern. The “check” is the threshold that a creature has to roll above on their D20. The “bonus” is everything that is added to the roll to try and get over that threshold.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The most common example of this pattern is the basic attack role. In attack roles, the check is called Armor Class (AC) and your bonus is appropriately called your Attack Bonus (which will be the sum of several individual bonuses, proficiency bonus, attribute modifier, weapon enchantment, etc). But note that the same Check-Bonus pattern applies to spell saving throws, where the check is called DC, and the bonus is your appropriate saving throw bonuses. Same goes for skill checks too.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For the Check-Bonus pattern we must first determine what number we have to roll above on the D20, then from there we need to express that as probability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hopefully the process of figuring out what number you need to roll above on the D20 is intuitive to you. Nevertheless, it will be useful for us to formalize it. I always refer to this value as “n,” where:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="n--check--bonus">n = (Check – Bonus)
&lt;/h4>&lt;p>Let’s try a quick example. Suppose Niles the rogue has a +5 Attack Bonus and is rolling to hit against an orc with a 16 AC, then “n = 16 – 5” or “n = 11” which just means that Niles must roll an 11 or above to hit the attack.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That is all well and good, but “11” isn’t a value that expresses a probability. In probability, values are expressed in percent (i.e. 15% chance to hit), which is more fundamentally expressed as a decimal (i.e. 0.15). Probability is always the number of desired outcomes divided by the number of total outcomes. We can find the number of desired outcomes by subtracting n from 20, then we divide that by 20 (which is the number of possible outcomes on a 20 sided dice). This new number (n expressed as a probability) I call “p”, thus:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="p--20--n20">p = (20 – n)/20
&lt;/h4>&lt;p>But there is actually a problem with this, which we will see if we try out the formula. Let’s return to the example of Niles attacking the orc and see how it works. In that scenario n = 11, so p = 9/20, or 0.45 (45%). This cannot be correct, because we know intuitively that rolling an 11 or above on a D20 should be a 50% chance of success (11 through 20 actually represents 10 possible outcomes out of 20, not 9. Try counting them out on your fingers and you will see). Where did the missing 0.05 go?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Remember that if n = 11 then a roll equal to or above 11 is what we need to succeed. It’s the “equal to” that we didn’t calculate in our formula. To account for this I just cheat and add 0.05 on at the end. So the corrected formula expressing n as probability is:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="p--20--n20--005">p = (20 – n)/20 + 0.05
&lt;/h4>&lt;p>In the majority of situations p is all we will need to determine our chance to hit. The minority of situations where p does not equal our chance to hit is in situations where there is advantage or disadvantage, so we will turn to calculating those next.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="advantage-and-disadvantage">Advantage and Disadvantage
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>In 5e, attacking with advantage means you roll your D20 twice and take the highest result. Conversely, disadvantage means you roll twice and take the lowest result. The math behind this seems daunting, at least it did for me, until I discovered this helpful way to think about it and model it. We’ll start with attack roles. First, some basic principles:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>When you are attacking with advantage, you must miss twice in a row to actually miss.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When you are attacking with disadvantage, you must HIT twice in a row to actually hit.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>We can model this with a very simple graph:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/85004da22c9406459458e015235194c1f200abf7-200x65.png?fm=webp&amp;amp;max-w=448"
loading="lazy"
alt="Adv_DsAdv_Chart"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Each box represents a possible outcome and we can easily picture what our hit percentage will be by shading in the outcomes which will translate to a hit (since what we want is our percentage chance to hit). Note, all four boxes together will equal the value “1” because they represent all possible outcomes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s easiest to start with disadvantage. When attacking with disadvantage we need to find the probability of the “Hit-Hit” outcome (see point 2 above), so we graph that by shading it in:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/d4c6eaf1ed97145df4ae897ce32ac134673ae474-201x65.png?fm=webp&amp;amp;max-w=448"
loading="lazy"
alt="DsAdv_Chart"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is actually very easy to calculate because we already know how to calculate our base chance to hit. To determine the chance of two outcomes you must multiply those outcomes together, in our case its two hits, so, “hit% x hit%” or “p x p” or “p2”. Let&amp;rsquo;s make a note of that for our list of formulas:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="formula-for-disadvantage-p2">Formula for disadvantage: p^2
&lt;/h4>&lt;p>Now what about when we are attacking with advantage? This is much more complicated to solve, but once we model it on our graph we can see what we need to do. Remember, when attacking with advantage you must miss twice to actually miss, so:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/1c882eaa6ee55316d059a7d628afc6fbe968afc4-199x65.png?fm=webp&amp;amp;max-w=448"
loading="lazy"
alt="Adv_Chart"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The easiest way to zero in on those three boxes is to find the value of the “Miss-Miss” box than subtract that number from 1. Why? Because, as we noted above, all four boxes together equal the value of 1 (or 100% chance, because when calculating odds 100%, expressed as 1, is the upper bound). If we find the exact value of the “Miss-Miss” box and subtract that from 1 we will have the value of the three shaded boxes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So what is the value of the “Miss-Miss&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; box? Well, it will be miss% squared (just like the “Hit-Hit box was hit% squared). The difficulty is we haven’t calculated for the miss equivalent of “p.” But it&amp;rsquo;s really not much of a difficulty, because we can just subtract p from 1 to get miss% (because if you aren’t hitting you are missing, there is no middle term). Thus,&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="miss--1--p">Miss% = 1 – p
&lt;/h4>&lt;p>Then we need to square that to isolate the value of the “Miss-Miss” box:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="miss-miss-box--1--p2">Miss-Miss Box = (1 – p)^2
&lt;/h4>&lt;p>Then we need to subtract that from 1 to isolate the value of the three shaded boxes:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="1--1--p2">1 – (1 – p)^2
&lt;/h4>&lt;p>And that is our formula for calculating our chance to hit when attacking with advantage!&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="formula-for-advantage-1--1--p2">Formula for Advantage: 1 – (1 – p)^2
&lt;/h4>&lt;p>Just for the sake of being thorough, what would the formula be in a “double-advantage” scenario, where you roll three dice and take the highest? This is possible in 5e with the Elven Accuracy feat. In these cases, nothing changes about the math except now you need three hits and three misses, so the formula stays the same except that everytime something is squared, we change it to the power of three, so:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="formula-for-double-advantage-1--1--p3">Formula for Double Advantage: 1 – (1 – p)^3
&lt;/h4>&lt;h2 id="attack-roles-dpr">Attack Roles (DPR)
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>That is all the basics covered. Now we can apply it. One of these easiest and most useful things to calculate in any tactical combat game is damage per round (DPR) on attack roles. 5e uses a standard 3-outcome system for attack roles – Hit, Miss, and Crit. Misses, of course, do no damage at all, so to calculate DPR we need to focus on hitting and critting. The core of the calculation is to multiply your chance for an outcome with the average damage on that outcome, then add that number for all outcomes together. When we do this we get the following formula:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="dpr--hit---crit-x-dmghit--crit-x-dmgcrit">DPR = (Hit% - Crit%) x dmg/hit + Crit% x dmg/crit
&lt;/h4>&lt;p>Here our Hit% will be equal to p (modified accordingly for advantage and disadvantage). The reason we subtract Crit% from it at the beginning is because when we were calculating p above we did not differentiate hitting from critting, so p actually includes both probabilities together until we subtract Crit% out of it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Still, there is something missing from this formula, and it is number of attacks in a round. What the above formula really represents is damage per attack, so we can just multiply the whole thing by attacks per round (APR) to get to a full DPR formula:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="dpr--hit---crit-x-dmghit--crit-x-dmgcrit-apr">DPR = ((Hit% - Crit%) x dmg/hit + Crit% x dmg/crit) APR
&lt;/h4>&lt;p>And, of course, if your build makes separate attacks on a bonus action, you will need to run the same formula for bonus actions and add that to the whole.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As a final note to finish this section off, I want to discuss the mathematics of critting. First off, what does a crit actually do? In D&amp;amp;D 5e a critical hit allows you to double all your damage dice when you roll damage. It does not double any flat bonuses that you have, for example, from your strength attribute or barbarian rage or even the Great Weapon Master (GWM) feat. That means your dmg/crit value will be a little less than double your dmg/hit, depending on your build and how much of your damage is coming from dice rolls. For a typical level 4 GWM fighter a crit will hover around a 35% boost to damage, for a typical level 4 rogue a crit will be around a 73% increase to damage, and for a level 4 wizard casting Chromatic Orb a crit will actually double your damage (100% increase).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s also important to remember that advantage/disadvantage modifies your crit percent as well. If you are rolling twice and taking the highest you will be critting more often as well as hitting more often! The contrary is true if you are attacking with disadvantage. Run the same formula on your base odds to crit to get your modified Crit% when attacking with advantage/disadvantage.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="spell-saves-dptr">Spell Saves (DPTr)
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Enough about attacks, what about spells? Spells by and large have many potent effects that are hard to mathematically model, so we won’t try to do that here. All you can really calculate on a spell like Hold Person is how likely you will be to land the spell on a target and how much it boosts the DPR of an ally to attack a paralyzed target. How valuable it is to lock down a target in a fight is more nebulous. Nonetheless, there are some spells that are just damage spells and understanding and comparing these is very straightforward.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 5e, most damage spells will fit into two kinds, which I call attack spells and save spells. An attack spell is just like attacking with a weapon, so the math is identical to what we outlined above. We won’t say anything more about them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Save spells are different. In a save spell you don’t roll to hit, instead, you impose your check (DC) against your target who rolls against it to avoid the effect. Because of this, it would feel contrived for save spells to crit (do you crit if they roll as 1? Its weird…). To compensate for not being able to crit, save spells do half damage on a miss.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As in the case of calculating attack roles, the formula will be multiplying your chance for an outcome with the average damage on that outcome, then add those numbers for all outcomes together. In this case we have two possible outcomes: hit and miss. Thus, our base formula will be:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="save-spell-damage--hit-x-dmghit--miss-x-dmgmiss">Save Spell Damage = Hit% x dmg/hit + Miss% x dmg/miss
&lt;/h4>&lt;p>That is the damage it will do to a single target though. Many spells, like Fireball for example, can hit more than one target. Thus:&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="save-spell-damage--hit-x-dmghit--miss-x-dmgmiss-targets">Save Spell Damage = (Hit% x dmg/hit + Miss% x dmg/miss) Targets
&lt;/h4>&lt;p>The thing is, its impossible to predict what the average targets hit will be. It will vary drastically by your group strategy and the amount of combatants you face in an encounter. For this reason, I prefer to compare damage spells by their damage per target stat (DPTr) and make a note of how effective their targeting method is. This is as far as out very simple calculations will get us, the rest is up to your own best judgement, and that is the really fun part!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="progression-and-flattened-math">Progression and Flattened Math
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>The last area of math that is fundamental to understanding 5e and BG3 has to do with character progression. That is, how much stronger does a character get from level 1 to level 20? To model this, let’s look at the very basic stats of Elanna the Fighter. At level 1 Elanna has 16 strength and constitution, is wearing chainmail armor, and wields a longsword and shield with the Dueling Fighting Style. Here are her basic combat stats:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Elanna (Lvl 1)&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Attack Bonus:&lt;/strong> +5&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Damage:&lt;/strong> 9.5, 14 on a crit&lt;br>
&lt;strong>APR:&lt;/strong> 1&lt;br>
&lt;strong>AC:&lt;/strong> 18&lt;br>
&lt;strong>HP:&lt;/strong> 13&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Fast forward 20 levels, and now Elanna has a 20 strength and constitution. In her adventures she acquired +3 plate armor, and a +3 longsword and shield (the highest level of enchantment). Here are the same stats at max level:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Elanna (Lvl 20)&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Attack Bonus:&lt;/strong> +14&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Damage:&lt;/strong> 14.5, 19 on a crit&lt;br>
&lt;strong>APR&lt;/strong>: 4&lt;br>
&lt;strong>AC:&lt;/strong> 26&lt;br>
&lt;strong>HP:&lt;/strong> 224&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can probably already see that the gains to attack bonus, damage, and armor class are not very high. The more important and impactful progression is in hit points and attacks per round. But let’s make the point clearer by comparing them to an enemy. Here are the basic stats of a Pit Fiend, an enemy Elanna might face at level 20:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Pit Fiend (CR 20)&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Attack Bonus:&lt;/strong> +14&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Damage:&lt;/strong> 19.5, 31 on a crit&lt;br>
&lt;strong>APR:&lt;/strong> 4&lt;br>
&lt;strong>AC:&lt;/strong> 19&lt;br>
&lt;strong>HP:&lt;/strong> 300&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Level 20 Elanna has an 80% chance to hit the Pit Fiend with an attack. But if Elanna fought the Pit Fiend at level 1, she would still have a 35% chance to hit it! 35% chance is not high, but it&amp;rsquo;s much higher than the 5% chance that we would expect from a level 1 character fighting a CR 20 monster.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Still though, it would take Lvl 20 Elanna 7 rounds on average to kill the Pit Fiend, whereas it would take Lvl 1 Elanna 85 rounds on average, a big difference! But what is the cause of it? Let’s try and isolate the variables. What if Lvl 20 Elanna only had 1 APR, in this situation it would take her 26 rounds on average to kill the Pit Fiend. However, Lvl 1 Elanna with 4 APR would kill it in 22. So, we can see that APR is BY FAR the most important factor in Elanna’s offensive progression.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What about her defensive progression? The Pit Fiend would kill Lvl 20 Elanna in 6 rounds on average and would kill Lvl 1 Elanna in 1. If level 1 Elanna had her level 20 armor and shield (26 AC) she would still die in 1 round. However, if she kept her 18 AC and instead had her level 20 HP she would survive 4 rounds on average. Tanking hits with HP is thus a more important part of Elanna’s defensive progression than avoiding them through AC. This is very different from other RPG systems like Pathfinder or 3e D&amp;amp;D where avoiding attacks is more potent.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The takeaway is this: that the potency of your attacks has a very stunted progression in 5e. Most progression comes from (1) making more attacks and (2) being able to tank more attacks. Elanna achieves this through stacking APR and HP, but a similar effect can be achieved by overwhelming enemies with sheer numbers. An army of goblins in 5e is a formidable encounter. Sure their attacks are weak, but they have so many of them, and that is what matters in 5e. This is why even weak summons are strong in 5e. The same principle is why it&amp;rsquo;s practically always better to find consistent uses for underused action types than it is to boost your standard action. Finding ways to make attacks with your bonus action and reaction every round is similar to boosting your APR.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Progression for spell casters is an entirely different story, that I don’t have the time to go into yet. The principles for it are not so different from what is standard in RPG’s, that progression is primarily found in the potency of the spells found at higher levels. Accuracy on your spells is very difficult to improve in 5e.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="list-of-formulas">List of Formulas
&lt;/h2>\[this is the number you have to roll at or above on D20\]\[this expresses n as a probability\]&lt;p>&lt;strong>Formula for disadvantage: p^2&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Formula for Advantage: 1 – (1 – p)^2&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Formula for Double Advantage: 1 – (1 – p)^3&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>DPR = ((Hit% - Crit%) x dmg/hit + Crit% x dmg/crit) APR&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>DPTr = (Hit% x dmg/hit + Miss% x dmg/miss) Targets&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles" >Return home&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Fallen Light - An Eagleheart Barbarian Build for BG3</title><link>https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/fallen-light-eagleheart-barbarian/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/fallen-light-eagleheart-barbarian/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/fallen-light-eagleheart-barbarian/seshtali_portrait.png" alt="Featured image of post Fallen Light - An Eagleheart Barbarian Build for BG3" />&lt;h1 id="guide-fallen-light---an-eagleheart-barbarian-build">Guide Fallen Light - An Eagleheart Barbarian Build
&lt;/h1>&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>“If thou beest she; But O how fall&amp;rsquo;n! how chang&amp;rsquo;d&lt;br>
From her, who in the happy Realms of Light&lt;br>
Cloth&amp;rsquo;d with transcendent brightness didst out-shine&lt;br>
Myriads though bright.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>From what highth fall&amp;rsquo;n, so much the stronger prov&amp;rsquo;d&lt;br>
She with her lightning: and till then who knew&lt;br>
The force of those dire arms? yet not for those,&lt;br>
Nor what the potent victor in her rage can else inflict on her foes.”&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>A new patch deserves a new build! Honestly, I’ve been testing out several new builds for the Barbarian, but this is the first one that just clicked. This build uses the new Eagleheart subclass in combination with a curated set out of items to rain lightning down from on high! And if there isn’t somewhere high to reign from, we can make our own throne.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If this is the first build of mine you are reading, I always write a unique character with a connection to the original Baldur’s Gate series, or Forgotten Realms lore in general, to fit all of my builds. Each character has their own themes and open questions that I leave for you to decide on your own runs. If you are interested in the build I hope you will check out the character as well!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-build">The Build
&lt;/h2>&lt;h3 id="overview">Overview
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Typically, what gets me interested in a build is a set of interesting mechanical interactions which might be hard for most players to notice. This build isn’t quite like that. Its central mechanics are less hidden, but do involve several new class features and items so for many players I am sure the combinations will be new.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Long time followers of my work will know how valuable lightning and frost damage are in BG3, thanks to Larian’s interpretation of the spell Create/Destroy Water. The wet condition from Create Water inflicts vulnerability to these two damage types and vulnerability, it turns out, is a very potent debuff. Last patch I released a build &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.aestusguides.com/guides/vlaakith-s-arcane-knight-of-faith-a-great-weapon-master-wizard-build" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>centered around maximizing retaliation frost damage from Armor of Agathys&lt;/a> in combination with Create Water. This build, similarly, maximizes the Lightning damage on wet targets in combination with highly accurate great weapon attacks for very high DPR.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Primarily, our lightning damage for this build will be coming from the interaction between a new enchanted set of boots – The Speedy Lightfeet – and the low-cost dashes we get from the Eagleheart barbarian subclass.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Speedy Lightfeet are part of a set of items that use a unique resource called “lightning charges.” While your character holds a charge, they get +1 to hit on their attack roles and deal +1 lightning damage on hits. Moreover, if they hit an attack while holding 5 charges or more, they will deal an additional 1d8 (4.5 average) lightning damage, consuming all of their charges. There are several ways to build lightning charges that correspond to the different items. The Speedy Lightfeet give you 3 charges whenever you dash, and that’s where the Eagleheart subclass enters the picture.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Eagleheart barbarians gain the ability to dash as a bonus action while they are raging. They also impose disadvantage on all opportunity attacks against them while they are raging. Their niche is blitzing past the front line of combat into melee range of priority backline targets. Besides all of that, we want this subclass so we can spam dashes for lightning charges to empower our attacks. If you use dash every round, you can be dealing, on average, 6.5 lightning damage every two rounds, or 3.25 per round. This is just the start!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We can add another 3.5 lightning damage per hit by wielding Light of Creation! This is a weapon a lot of folks seem to overlook. I don’t blame them; I overlooked it for a long time too, because if you just read the description it seems like it&amp;rsquo;s bad when in fact its quite good! It’s a +1 Halberd that does an additional 1d6 lightning damage each hit, however, there is also a chance (around 20%) that the wielder will be stunned when they hit a target. Losing a turn is not worth all the damage this weapon deals, or at least it wouldn’t be IF you lost a turn. The thing is you don’t. There is no way to know this without testing, but the stun condition ends as soon as you start your next turn. And remember, it triggers after you hit an attack, so the only action you risk losing from the stun is, possibly, your bonus action. Of course, until you next turn enemies do have advantage on attacks against you, but that doesn’t matter to our barbarian who spams Reckless Attack. Enemies have advantage to attack us anyways, and advantage never stacks!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So, adding it all up, we’ll deal around 7 extra lightning damage every hit. Attacking wet targets makes that 14! Add the +2 from Rage, +3 from strength, and base weapon damage and we average 25.5 damage per hit, attacking with advantage on every strike, and without any lost accuracy from Great Weapon Master. We’re going to combine this with an overload of Mobility for a blitzkrieg assault. We will run in, dish out our 25 damage, then retreat out of range of any attacks, and we can do this every round.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="level-1">Level 1
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Race:&lt;/strong> Barbarians want as many physical attribute boosts as they can grab, with a priority on strength, then constitution, and lastly dexterity. Resistances are also very valuable for barbarians, because resistances are a multiplier on health, and barbs have a lot of health. These conditions narrow down our list to a few top options:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Shield Dwarf, gets the best possible physical attribute boosts for the barbarian. They also get poison resistance, which is probably the best resistance outside of the physical damage types, which barbarians have anyways. Shield Dwarf is the optimal choice for every barbarian build, and likely will remain that way.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, there are other racial choices which are almost as good. Humans are great for barbarians because of the 16 in all three physical stats. Strongheart Halflings are great too, also getting the poison resistance and a +3 total bonuses to physical stats. Finally, Zariel Tieflings make great barbarians with their +1 strength and fire resistance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nevertheless, I chose to go with Wood Half-Elf for this build. Half-elves can get a 16 in strength and constitution, keep them on curve with those stats, but they also get bonus movement speed, which are always great on strikers, and gets doubled on this build from the dash spam. It&amp;rsquo;s not the optimal choice, but it was still strong.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Attributes:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Str: 16&lt;br>
Dex: 14&lt;br>
Con: 16&lt;br>
Int: 8&lt;br>
Wis: 8&lt;br>
Cha: 10&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Class:&lt;/strong> Barbarian&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Background and Skills:&lt;/strong> The only mandatory skill is Atheletics. Intimidate is also good for barbarians, they will get a lot of opportunities to use it. You can get both from soldier background. I went Outlander. If you want to solo with this build, take Charlatan.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="level-2">Level 2
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>There aren’t any decisions to make at this level. Just collect your Reckless Attack and Danger Sense.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="level-3">Level 3
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Here is where we choose our subclass, and, of course, we will be taking Eagleheart. This is also the level where we can get our first key item – The Speedy Lightfeet – which can be found under the windmill in the Blighted Village.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is another item worth mentioning just a stone’s throw away from the village, and that is Reason’s Grasp, a new pair of gauntlets exclusive to the Barbarian. These gauntlets give you 15 temporary hit points whenever you choose to end your Rage and ending it automatically after a fight counts! In my runs, I never have fights go long enough for my Rage to actually time out, so this is a practically guaranteed 15 temporary hit points per rage, or 45 extra hit points total. That is doubling our hit points! I hope you weren’t wanting to die at all because it won’t happen now.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="level-4">Level 4
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>The big decision at this level is what feat we want to choose. We’re going to take a rare feat option: Mobile. This feat adds 3m to our movement speed, makes us immune to difficult terrain when we dash, and makes us immune to opportunity attacks on rounds where we move after we attack. Congrats, you are the flash now! With this feat and a few other buffs we can reach 39m of movement per round while raging. Yes, you read that right, that’s 39m, not 39ft. With this amount of movement we can run in, attack, then run out while still being far enough away that the average dashing enemy can’t reach us.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you would prefer not to go Mobile, Great Weapon Master and a +2 strength ASI are also good choices.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now that we are at max level we can collect all of our key items. The easiest to grab is the Ring of Crusher, which we can get off of Crusher’s corpse in the goblin village. This ring increases our movement by 3m.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Light of Creation can be found in the Mage Tower in the underdark. You’ll have to take it from Bernard, which can be a tough fight. There is a trick to make it much easier, but I won’t spoil the fun for you. While we are at the tower, we can pick up Sparkswall, a nifty ring that does synergize a ton with this build, but fits with it thematically.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, there is the question of our helmet slot. The Helm of Grit is the go to for martials, and with it we can double dash in a round, adding even more lightning damage! However, there are a lot of builds that want the Helm of Grit, and the combination of our overloaded mobility and durability makes it so we are seldom below 50%. For those reasons, I’m going to recommend you take Lifebringer (which can be bought from Blurg in the Myconid Colony). This is another item that works off of Lightning Charges, giving us 3 temporary hit points every time we gain charges, which for us is every turn. These temp hit points stack with the ones we get from Reason’s Grasp, and actually “heal” up the overall pool for some reason, so you can think of it as a 3 hit point regeneration effect, which is awesome!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Those are the key items.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="tactics">Tactics
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>This is a textbook hit-and-run build. Take out targets that have ranged attacks or crowd control first. Always run away and end your turn far enough from the melee enemies that they have to dash to reach you. With good positioning, they will waste a lot of their actions just dashing around the fight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Don’t forget, you are also extremely tanky, so if enemies do attack you, it&amp;rsquo;s not the end of the world. Sometimes it is worthwhile to let them reach you in order to split their position. Splitting enemy position is when you lead one group of enemies more than their standard movement in distance away from the rest of their group. After doing this, you can leave them to attack the other enemies. The distance you can cover with one movement might take them three of four, so they will waste their turns just moving while you attack their allies. These are the kind of opportunities you should look for.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here is a little trick. I am not sure where to put it, so I will just put it here. You can use Diving Strike without needing the elevation if you carry a few boxes along with you at all times. Just stack them up, make steps to the top if you need. It&amp;rsquo;s like a portable perch! You can use it to get an extra 9m of movement on your turn if, for some ungodly reason, the 39m you have wasn’t enough. I believe the prone condition automatically breaks concentration, so you can use it for that as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I did make this build with a team in mind. For example, to reach the 39m move per turn, you’ll need Gale to cast Longstrider, and you will need Shadowheart to cast Create Water. Try to build your team composition with mobility in mind as well. Basically, make sure the other three members of your party are good ranged attacks. I still recommend Lae’zel, but don’t rush her in right away. It&amp;rsquo;s okay to stay hidden to force aggro on Tav for a round or two. Doing this will give them no option but to chase Tav all over, making it easier to split them.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="performance">Performance
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>As is tradition, let’s see how this build compares to my builds in the past:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/fallen-light-eagleheart-barbarian/fallen_light_dpr.png"
width="480"
height="289"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/fallen-light-eagleheart-barbarian/fallen_light_dpr_hu_75ce60324479e066.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/fallen-light-eagleheart-barbarian/fallen_light_dpr_hu_3e00ca39f57b2383.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Fallen Light DPR"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="166"
data-flex-basis="398px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this graph you can see two curves, one for how it does when attacking normally and another for how it does when attacking wet targets. Its damage curve just gets better the higher AC the enemies get. In this regard its like The Brand build, only it performs better.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As I noted in the build overview the Knight of Faith build also got a significant boost to DPR from casts of Create Water, so let&amp;rsquo;s look at how Fallen Light compares to Knight of Faith specifically:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/fallen-light-eagleheart-barbarian/fallen_light_vs_knight_of_faith_dpr.png"
width="480"
height="289"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/fallen-light-eagleheart-barbarian/fallen_light_vs_knight_of_faith_dpr_hu_7b0f586fe67224d0.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/fallen-light-eagleheart-barbarian/fallen_light_vs_knight_of_faith_dpr_hu_813640ef8cc6f630.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Fallen Light vs Knight of Faith DPR"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="166"
data-flex-basis="398px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So…. The Knight of Faith did a lot of damage with Armor of Agathys. Fallen Light has an advantage in its target selection and consistency, but is it enough of an advantage to outweigh the sheer volume of damage the Knight of Faith puts out? Probably not. It&amp;rsquo;s honestly hard to judge because of how these builds function so differently. The Knight of Faith was a Juggernaut of tankiness and damage, whereas Fallen Light is all about fast attacks and gaining positional advantages through movement.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My judgement right now is that Fallen Light is somewhere between The Brand and The Knight of Faith in power. In a lot of ways, it’s a better version of The Brand as far as its tactical niche goes. I think it&amp;rsquo;s possible that this build could be an S-tier, but until I have more experience with its unusual tactics I will be ranking it an “A.” It is a better A-tier build than The Brand though.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/fallen-light-eagleheart-barbarian/seshtali_portrait.png"
width="551"
height="637"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/fallen-light-eagleheart-barbarian/seshtali_portrait_hu_54b206b7b0c90e9a.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/fallen-light-eagleheart-barbarian/seshtali_portrait_hu_b7e72e33a99fcf4e.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Seshtali"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="86"
data-flex-basis="207px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-character---seshtali">The Character - Seshtali
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>From Baldur’s Gate 2: Throne of Bhaal epilogue:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Aerie and Charname would prove inseparable, their adventuring careers becoming secondary to the raising of their son, and eventually a daughter as well. Their later years would hold one last great trek, however, as Aerie still suffered a sadness from her time enslaved and the loss of her wings. Together she and Charname sought the avariel of Faenya-Dail, the winged elves she was stolen from so long ago. They discovered not only her people, but loving parents that had spent years searching for their lost child. With no more mystery or confusion to cloud their lives, it was there, among the clouds, that Aerie and Charname would finally be married. Their union, it is said, was blessed by visions of Aerdrie Faenya and Baervan Wildwanderer both.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These heroes fought through the depths of hell to the heights of the heavens. Yet hell stains even the virtuous. Can it be that the son of Bhaal carries not the seed of murder whither he goes? Thus he foretold, “which way I fly is hell, myself am hell; and in even the glorified heights the lowest deep still threatens to devour me: that the hell I suffer seems a heaven…”&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And thus he departed the marble palaces of Faenya-Dail; with his right shoulder to the rising sun and his back to his family he descended. So it was that bitterness entered the heart of Seshtali, the seed of Bhaal on Toril, just as bitterness is the seed of wrath.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The peaks of Faenya-Dail embraced the highest clouds of the heavens. There the avariel erected empyrean palaces of a hundred pilastered arches. At its center, nestled in a cleft of the marble cliffs, an arcadian colonnade served as the community&amp;rsquo;s public square. There the pastoral avarial traded their works of art amongst each other. Food was neither scarce nor abundant, for the marble cliffs, while glorious, were barren. Nevertheless, the avariel needed little for food, and their winged hunters labored well, and much time remained for the enjoyment of art, and song, and sport.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The young Seshtali longed to hunt, but she could not, for she had no wings. Her time was spent in study, which she detested, tutored by her mother in the hallowed halls of the Vaunted Basilica, which perched on the highest peak of the mountain. In the evenings, she would climb the cliffs, looking for prey until the sun set. There the young avariel would tease her, and Seshtali felt wrath welling up within her. Wrath, yes, and hate, and… desire. Visions disrupted her sleep; nightmares of bone and blood. Or were they dreams?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>She was still an adolescent when she fell. It began with a storm, rolling in from the south as she climbed. She hastily made for home, a group of boys watched on, mocking her. Their jeers made her lose focus, and she slipped, falling gracelessly and landing hard on her back. She tried to gasp, but her breath had left her, so she sputtered and choked for air while the boys laughed and flew away. She was lying there crying when rain began to fall.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The climb back was dangerous in the wet, but Seshtali’s grip did not slip. It could not slip. Her rage drove her, strengthening her arm and sharpening her focus. She gloried in it. And just as she scaled the final face, she spied her tormentors alight on the steps of the basilica. &lt;em>They go to pray to Aerdrie for protection&lt;/em>, she thought. It was customary for the young boys to pray for safety for their fathers who were hunting during a storm. Seshtali grinned, laying hold of a loose rock, and stalked them into the temple. The rage rushed up to her again, and the hate, and the desire. Brutally she slew them, and she reveled in it, the blood and bone. It felt to her at that moment that she was born for blood as the avariel were born to fly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>“Sesh! What have you done…”&lt;/p>
&lt;p>She turned. It was Quayle, her brother. “What are you doing here?” She asked.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>“I came to pray for father.”&lt;/p>
&lt;p>“He is not out hunting. He left us,” she responded bitterly. Quayle did not approach her, he looked to the bloodied rock in her hand.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>“Did you do this? You killed them…” She could see fear and confusion in his eyes at first, then there was something else there, something she had not seen in him before. After a moment, it dawned on her: disgust. She gripped the rock tighter. Rain poured onto the vaulted dome above. Quayle tensed, turning to flee, when a clap of lightning struck nearby, startling him. In a flash, Seshtali launched the bloody missile and with a snap it struck his skull. He crumpled to the marble floor and she knew that he was dead.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Seshtali fled Faenya-Dail that day, under the cover of the storm no one could track her. She lived in the wild, instinct her tutor and wrath her terrible weapon. Thus did she wander, with her right shoulder to the rising sun.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="role-playing-notes-for-seshtali">Role Playing Notes for Seshtali
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>I of course wrote Seshtali to be a direct continuation of the story of the original Baldur’s Gate series. Similarly, she directly continues the themes of both Aerie and the main character from those games. Aerie was fallen in the literal sense, a winged elf who had lost her wings and had to come to terms with the ugliness of earth. She was fragile, like a bird, and had to become strong. The player character from Baldur’s Gate was fallen in a metaphorical sense. Or, at least, he struggles not to fall, depending on the choices you make. The point is the ever present allure of violence and power; you decide whether you fight it or succumb. Its not meaningless that the entire series began with this quote from Nietzsche: &amp;ldquo;He who fights with monsters might take care lest he thereby become a monster. And if you gaze for long into an abyss, the abyss gazes also into you.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Seshtali has the same blood of Bhaal, and thus suffers the same allure, something the game writers themselves bring up when Quayle is born in Throne of Bhaal. For Seshtali in BG3, there are a lot of ways this allure can play out concretely.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, through the mechanics of the barbarian class. Barbarians are all about violence and rage, and for Seshtali we can view this as tapping into her birthright of murder, like the Slayer form in BG2.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Second, in our reaction to the Cult of the Absolute. It is clear that the resurrected Bhaal is tied to this new cult. How will the granddaughter of Bhaal react to that? Does she hate Bhaal? Is she loyal to him? Perhaps she wants to replace him.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Third, in our interaction with the tadpole powers. How will Seshtali react to the seductive powers the tadpole offer us? Its a mirror, in a way, to the seductive powers of her bloodline.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All of these questions bring us to the driving question of the entire character: why did Seshtali run? Or, the same question another way, how does Seshtali feel about murdering her brother? Clearly there is a part of her - the Bhaal part of her - that savors it, like (her uncle) Sarevok. Did she embrace murder and flee her home to be free of their repressive constraints? Or is murdering her own brother the moment that snapped her out of her bloodlust and she fled because of her guilt and shame? I leave that for you to decide!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>If you want to discuss this build or the character with me and others &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.aestusguides.com/guides/fallen-light-an-eagleheart-barbarian-build" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>you can do so here.&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you are interested in more content like this, please check out &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.patreon.com/user?u=52365991&amp;amp;fan_landing=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>my Patreon&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles" >Return home&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Baldur's Gate 3 Weapons Tier List - Patch 7</title><link>https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/Greatsword_PlusOne_Icon.png" alt="Featured image of post Baldur's Gate 3 Weapons Tier List - Patch 7" />&lt;h1 id="guide-baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list">Guide Baldur&amp;rsquo;s Gate 3 Weapons Tier List
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>Patch 7 is live! I am releasing this tier list while my game is updating, so all of this information is already outdated. Nevertheless, I want you all to have it for your Patch 7 runs! I will be updating it to include any new weapons that have been added as quickly as I can, so check in again in a few days!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This article is actually two tier lists in one. I rank all the unique weapons in the game, but I also rank Larian&amp;rsquo;s added weapon actions. Both are important to understanding what you will get from your weapon choices.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you are thinking “I can probably figure out the relative usefulness of these weapons by reading their wiki entries. I don’t need Aestus to tell me which weapons are good.” You are both right and wrong. You are right that you don’t need me to tell you what is good (although I hope you find my opinions interesting at least!). Where you are wrong is that you cannot really know much just by reading wiki descriptions. Many of these weapons do not do what they say they do, including some of your favorites, like the Staff of Arcane Blessing. I painstakingly tested these weapons to find out what they actually do. So even if you understand what makes a weapon good in BG3, you can probably still learn a lot from this article. Even after all my testing, I am sure I missed some things or made some mistakes. If you catch something I missed, let me know and I will update the article.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="weapon-actions">Weapon Actions
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>If you are new to BG3 you may be wondering what weapon actions are. Weapon Actions are simple activatable abilities that you can use once per short rest and are tied to the weapon you use. They were added to BG3 by Larian, so you won’t find them in other 5th edition games.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Because they were added so recently, there is a lot of confusion surrounding these actions. The tooltips do not clear anything up; most weapon actions work very differently than what their tooltip says. I have tested all of them and tried my best to write a clearer description than what is offered in the game. Read them over, some of them may surprise you! I also rank them in a tier system because that’s just what I do!&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="tiers">Tiers
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Here is what the tiers mean:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>S Tier:&lt;/strong> Consistently amazing weapon actions. These are game changing actions that are perhaps in need of a nerf. Use these often.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>A Tier:&lt;/strong> Consistently good weapon actions. These aren’t game changing but they are useful in most fights and are nice to have.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>B Tier:&lt;/strong> Consistently average weapon actions. B-tier weapon actions are underwhelming, but still technically useful in most situations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>C Tier:&lt;/strong> Weapon actions that can be useful in niche circumstances but are usually not worth the resource you expend to use them. These could be removed from the game and no one should really notice.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>RP Tier:&lt;/strong> For a weapon action that is actually useless. You don’t get any advantage from using this ability. Larian needs to rework this into something that actually does something.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Many weapon actions require a target to make a saving throw, and thus have a DC. With one exception (Backbreaker) Weapon Action DC = 10 + Proficiency Bonus + Strength/Dexterity Modifier.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here is a &lt;a class="link" href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1NpwOx9Q2agMM_93KIIs0Y52iIzDymI4L9YqdGfpR8Mc/edit?usp=sharing" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>reference sheet&lt;/a> for which weapons get which actions:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ok, let’s get to the list!&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="backbreaker---b-tier">Backbreaker - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/backbreaker.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/backbreaker_hu_3a6a19e2d4cde4d9.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/backbreaker_hu_9ad68140afaeeff7.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Backbreaker"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The character makes a single standard attack as an action. If the attack hits it deals damage as normal but as if your weapon has 1d4 base damage. Moreover, the target must make a strength saving throw or be knocked prone for two turns. A prone target has disadvantage on strength and dexterity saving throws and all attacks against the target made within 3m have advantage. A target may stand up at the cost of half of its movement.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: For some reason Backbreaker has a lower DC than all of the other weapon actions. Instead of 10 + Proficiency Bonus + Strength/Dexterity Modifier it has 8 + Proficiency Bonus + Strength/Dexterity Modifier, a -2 penalty.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With this ability you lose a bit of damage and get a (slim) chance of knocking the target prone (slim because this is a double-hit ability; you have to hit the attack and the saving throw to gain full effect). Prone is an average status condition. The best thing you get from it is advantage on attacks, but on their next turn they will just stand up again, so only use this if you have an ally who can attack before they stand back up.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="brace---c-tier">Brace - C Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/brace.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/brace_hu_657f51894bf3633f.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/brace_hu_a3493b88920697c3.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Brace"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You spend 7.5m of movement and for the rest of your turn you roll damage twice and use the highest result.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This ability seems good until you do the math on what rolling damage twice actually does. It adds, on average, 1.65 damage per hit (1.31 for the Longbow). Being able to spend movement (which you often don’t need) to but damage is great, but the damage is just so underwhelming.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="cleave---b-tier">Cleave - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/cleave.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/cleave_hu_d27b3756ea05bccd.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/cleave_hu_8a02e9ad9faf0ef8.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Cleave"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You attack in a cone that can hit up to 3 targets in front of you. For every attack that hits you deal half of your normal attack damage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When I released this article I had this ranked C-tier. I&amp;rsquo;ve realized now I completely missed the mark with that ranking. The error in my earlier analysis was that I didn&amp;rsquo;t realize it doesn&amp;rsquo;t half flat damage bonuses from sources like Great Weapon Master or Rage. From what I can tell, it halves all damage dice (whether the base damage of the weapon or extra sources like dipped weapons) and it halves your ability modifier (the bonus damage from strength). Everything else is not halved. So it actually does do more damage than a normal hit if you can hit at least two targets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you have Great Weapon Master, this is an A-tier action. For everyone else its a B.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="concussive-smash---s-tier">Concussive Smash - S Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/concussive_smash.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/concussive_smash_hu_64e1559a28d99124.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/concussive_smash_hu_f84dab529110bf7.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Concussive Smash"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The character makes a standard attack as an action. If the attack hits the target must make a constitution saving throw or receive the dazed condition for two turns. A dazed creature has disadvantage on wisdom saving throws, cannot take reactions, and loses their dexterity bonus to armor class.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dazed is an overpowered status condition. Wisdom save spells are the most potent (Tasha’s, Hold Person, etc), so imposing disadvantage on wisdom saves is already enough to make this good. Add on that the target also loses their dexterity bonus to AC and we are in OP territory now. This makes a perfect set-up for Menacing Strike (with an action surge), which is already one of the best control features in the game. Even with all of that, this is still the weakest S-tier weapon action. Keep reading!&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="crippling-strike---b-tier">Crippling Strike - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/crippling_strike.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/crippling_strike_hu_618d2d434c437982.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/crippling_strike_hu_e268f12c7758bbba.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Crippling Strike"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The character makes a single standard attack as an action. If the attack hits it deals damage as normal but as if your weapon has 1d4 base damage. Moreover, the target must make a constitution saving throw or receive the crippled condition for two turns. A crippled target’s movement is reduced to 0 and they have disadvantage on dexterity saving throws.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A slightly better version of Backbreaker. Not good enough to move it into A-tier.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="flourish---b-tier">Flourish - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/flourish.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/flourish_hu_5746bb5c2ab709fd.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/flourish_hu_3f74899670903708.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Flourish"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Flourish is like a melee range control spell that takes a bonus action to cast. The target must make a dexterity saving throw or receive the condition off-balance for two turns. A creature that is off-balance has disadvantage on strength saving throws and the next attack against them is made with advantage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Off-balance is a mediocre condition but being able to apply it on a bonus action is great! Use this to set up a sneak attack or another, stronger weapon action.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="hamstring-shot---b-tier">Hamstring Shot - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/hamstring_shot.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/hamstring_shot_hu_6c4d1d6964f3309b.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/hamstring_shot_hu_50aaec335e3892c8.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Hamstring Shot"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Make a standard attack. If the attack hits you deal damage as normal, but the target must also roll a constitution saving throw. If they fail, they acquire the hamstrung condition. A hamstrung target has their movement reduced by 50%.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Reducing movement by half… Who cares? Technically its useful for kiting, buts it’s a single target once per short rest, and kiting is something you need to do more frequently than that. Still, there is no reduced damage on this ability, so there is no drawback to using it. Its just a standard attack with a mediocre added effect.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="heartstopper---s-tier">Heartstopper - S Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/heartstopper.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/heartstopper_hu_6d45fd4b1d3139d3.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/heartstopper_hu_d87a4c93d4a0d0c9.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Heartstopper"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The character makes a single standard attack as an action. If the attack hits it deals damage as normal but as if your weapon has 1d4 base damage. Moreover, the target must make a constitution saving throw or receive the chest trauma condition for two turns. A target with chest trauma has disadvantage on constitution saving throws and loses their standard action.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Not enough people are talking about how overpowered Heartstopper is. The enemy loses their action for two turns… TWO TURNS OF NO ACTION. If that doesn’t sound amazing to you, I won’t be able to explain it. Keep a morning-star on every martial character to use this on boss fights or big monsters.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="lacerate---b-tier">Lacerate - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/lacerate.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/lacerate_hu_f7a4e87f6eea73ea.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/lacerate_hu_8ebd8cdda27a358b.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Lacerate"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is made as a part of a standard attack. If the attack hits the target takes damage as normal but also must make a constitution saving throw to acquire the bleeding condition for two rounds. A bleeding creature takes two slashing damage at the beginning of their turn and has disadvantage on constitution saving throws.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is one of the stronger B-tier abilities. The extra damage is meh. Constitution save disadvantage is real reason to use this. Constitution save spells (Thunderwave, Ray of Enfeeblement, Shatter, Moonbeam, etc) are not as powerful as wisdom save spells, but they can still swing a fight.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="mobile-shot---rp-tier">Mobile Shot - RP Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/mobile_shot.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/mobile_shot_hu_7ed6bed1125fc374.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/mobile_shot_hu_33f9fedc538ca41.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Mobile Shot"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When you use your dash action you may make a standard attack as a bonus action.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is another one that sounds good until you think it over. Its exclusive to hand crossbows, whose niche is being the dual-wield ranged weapon. Dual wielding already allows you make an attack with your bonus action. If you aren’t going to dual wield your hand crossbow then why use a hand crossbow? That is its only advantage over other crossbows. There is absolutely no use for this weapon action.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="piercing-strikeshot---a-tier">Piercing Strike/Shot - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/piercing_strike.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/piercing_strike_hu_ff840ddef2a79530.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/piercing_strike_hu_7f471f8a6760a87a.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Piercing Strike"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The character makes a single standard attack as an action. If the attack hits the target must make a constitution saving throw or receive the gaping wounds condition for two turns. A target with gaping wounds takes an additional two piercing damage when hit by an attack. Gaping wounds is removed if the target is healed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is my favorite weapon action. Not because it’s the best, but because it’s the most fun to play around with. Gaping wounds deals more damage the more hits you can get against a target. So how many hits can you get in a single turn? Here are the current standings:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Circlet of Fire sorcerer, triple cast of Scorching Ray – 9 hits (18 bonus damage)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Circlet of Fire Thief, dual wielding + Scorching Ray Scroll – 6 hits (12 bonus damage)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Circlet of Fire Warlock, dual wielding + Scorching Ray – 5 hits (10 bonus damage)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>The first two are really niche circumstances, but the third is actually practical. I’ve had 5 attack rounds often with a warlock. One of the most reliable ways of dealing high single target damage is with Scorching Ray because it benefits from Mystra’s Blessing, high ground bonus, the easy stealth advantage, and Circlet of Fire. With dual hand crossbows, you can set up on a target with Piercing Shot and Hex, then, next turn, blast them with Scorching Ray and two off-hand shots, each procing the bonus damage from Hex and gaping wounds, for an average of 5.5 bonus damage per hit (the full combo will average 61.5 damage assuming all attacks hit and a 16-17 dexterity).&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="prepare---a-tier">Prepare - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/prepare.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/prepare_hu_54a142876942e98f.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/prepare_hu_fbdce1850e11830d.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Prepare"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You spend 7.5m of movement to add your strength modifier in slashing damage with your weapon till the end of your turn (i.e. it effectively doubles your strength modifier for damage).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Like Piercing Strike, this ability is fun because of how you can multiply it. You multiply your strength by two, then multiply it again by the number of hits in your turn. On a Great Weapon Master build you can attack at max twice in a turn, meaning every +1 bonus to your strength modifier will do a possible +4 damage with Prepare. Its possible to have a 22 strength (18 base + 4 from potions), which is a +6 modifier, or +24 damage just from strength alone. Of course, only half of that is coming from Prepare, but you get the idea.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="pommel-strike---s-tier">Pommel Strike - S Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/pommel_strike.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/pommel_strike_hu_6a220dace128cbcf.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/pommel_strike_hu_773c0d05adffa9b7.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Pommel Strike"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pommel Strike makes an attack role as a bonus action. If the attack hits the target takes you strength modifier in damage and must also make a constitution saving throw or become dazed for 2 rounds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is like a low damage Concussive Smash, but you can use it on a bonus action. That means you can inflict daze and make a Menacing Strike on the same turn without using action surge. If you do use action surge, you can Menacing Strike twice (if the first one misses). If you are in the same initiative as your wizard, you can Pommel Strike to set up his Tasha’s, and then attack for a free crit. This ability is so good you should never take a short rest before using it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="rush-attack---a-tier">Rush Attack - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/rush_attack.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/rush_attack_hu_4c997924bd69b70b.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/rush_attack_hu_24091e7129ee4d75.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Rush Attack"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As an action you can charge 9m forward in a straight line and attack a target. If the attack hits it deals damage as normal but as if your weapon has 1d4 base damage. On a hit the target must also make a strength save or be knocked off-balance for two rounds. A creature that is off-balance has disadvantage on strength saving throws and the next attack against them is made with advantage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We discussed off-balance above when we were analyzing Flourish. Its not a great status effect, but its not bad either. The really impactful part of Rush Attack is that you get to move 9m on your action, likely doubling your movement, allowing you to close onto that pesky spell caster on their back lines. This ability does what Mobile Shot was trying to do.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="tenacity---c-tier">Tenacity - C Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/tenacity.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/tenacity_hu_a14651c00ded242f.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/tenacity_hu_4763aa45b94a45f2.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Tenacity"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you miss an attack, you may spend your reaction to deal your strength modifier in damage anyways.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The damage is low and it costs your reaction. At its best its 5 or so extra damage per short rest. Underwhelming, but technically not useless.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="topple---b-tier">Topple - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/topple.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/topple_hu_1b43d3e60196a57b.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/topple_hu_f41cd0f7a2afc07c.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Topple"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The target makes a dexterity saving throw. If they fail they are knocked prone for two rounds. A prone target has disadvantage on strength and dexterity saving throws and all attacks against the target made within 3m have advantage. A target may stand up at the cost of half of its movement.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since this is unique to staffs, its functions as an escape for your squishy caster. That is nice to have. It doesn’t require an attack role either, which really helps. This weapon action does its job.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="weakening-strike---b-tier">Weakening Strike - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/weakening_strike.png"
width="150"
height="150"
srcset="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/weakening_strike_hu_f48ede2ca4dc4ea5.png 480w, https://www.aestusguides.com/articles/baldurs-gate-3-weapons-tier-list/weakening_strike_hu_1f6723076e5834df.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Weakening Strike"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="240px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The character makes a single standard attack as an action. If the attack hits it deals damage as normal but as if your weapon has 1d4 base damage. Moreover, the target must make a strength saving throw or receive the weak grip condition for two turns. A target with weak grip has disadvantage on attack roles and strength saving throws.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I’m not impressed with weak grip as a condition. Strength saving throws are rare (Entangle, Ensnaring Strike, Backbreaker). Disadvantage on attack roles is good, but not fight changing, and it takes to hits to get that effect. Not useless, but not great either.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="weapon-actions-final-rankings">Weapon Actions Final Rankings
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>&lt;strong>S Tier:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Concussive Smash, Heartstopper, Pommel Strike&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>A Tier:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Flourish, Piercing Strike/Shot, Prepare, Rush Attack&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>B Tier:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Backbreaker, Crippling Strike, Hamstring Shot, Lacerate, Topple, Weakening Strike&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>C Tier:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Brace, Cleave, Tenacity&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>RP Tier:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mobile Shot&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="list-of-conditions">List of Conditions
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Bleeding:&lt;/strong> A bleeding creature takes two slashing damage at the beginning of their turn and has disadvantage on constitution saving throws.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Chest Trauma:&lt;/strong> A target with chest trauma has disadvantage on constitution saving throws and loses their standard action.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Crippled:&lt;/strong> A crippled target’s movement is reduced to 0 and they have disadvantage on dexterity saving throws.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Dazed:&lt;/strong> A dazed creature has disadvantage on wisdom saving throws, cannot take reactions, and loses their dexterity bonus to armor class.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Gaping Wounds:&lt;/strong> A target with gaping wounds takes an additional two piercing damage when hit by an attack. Gaping wounds is removed if the target is healed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Hamstrung&lt;/strong>: A hamstrung target has their movement reduced by 50%.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Off-Balance:&lt;/strong> A creature that is off-balance has disadvantage on strength and saving throws and the next attack against them is made with advantage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Prone:&lt;/strong> A prone target has disadvantage on strength and dexterity saving throws and all attacks against the target made within 3m have advantage. A target may stand up at the cost of half of its movement.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Weak Grip:&lt;/strong> A target with weak grip has disadvantage on attack roles and saving throws.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="unique-weapons-tier-list">Unique Weapons Tier List
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Now let’s turn our attention to the unique weapons in the game. As is customary, I’ll begin with some important disclaimers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By “unique weapons&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo; I mean weapons (and shields) that have a unique enchantment. The focus of this article is testing and ranking unique mechanics on weapons. There are some non-magical items that have a unique look or name – like the scrap sword or whipping cane – these are not included. Similarly, there are enchanted weapons that are not unique, like a simple +1 dagger, or any generic +1 weapon, these aren’t included. I do not include Phalar Aluve, because even though it has a unique look and name, mechanically it’s just a generic +1 longsword. Conversely, I do include the +1 Light Hammer that you can get at the forge outside the magic tower because even though it has a generic name, it does have a unique, mechanical enchantment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I’ve left out info on how to get these items to avoid spoilers. If you don’t care about that being spoiled, &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/BaldursGate3/comments/wcp34b/baldurs_gate_3_relevant_items_spreadsheet_updated/?utm_source=share&amp;amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;amp;context=3" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>this redditer&lt;/a> has already compiled a full list of unique items and where to acquire them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I will say it again in case you skipped the intro, if you are thinking “I can probably figure out the relative usefulness of these weapons by reading their wiki entries. I don’t need Aestus to tell me which weapons are good.” I will remind you, &lt;strong>many of these weapons do not do what they say they do&lt;/strong>, including some of your favorites, like the Staff of Arcane Blessing. I painstakingly tested these weapons to find out what they actually do.Even after all my testing, I am sure I missed some things or made some mistakes. If you catch something I missed, let me know and I will update the article.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="tiers-1">Tiers
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>&lt;strong>S Tier:&lt;/strong> Consistently amazing weapons; sometimes weapons worth building your character/party around, or ones that offer something important to already optimal strategies. Basically, they offer something potent that you can’t duplicate in another way. I try to get these weapons as soon as possible on my runs&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>A Tier:&lt;/strong> Consistently good or situationally amazing weapons. These are powerful weapons, still good enough to use as your main weapon. Some of them are good as side-arms that you swap into for certain situations. They are great, but not as game-changing as S-tier.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>B Tier:&lt;/strong> Just average weapons. As a general rule, B-tier weapons are close in power to a generic +1 weapon of the same type.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>C Tier:&lt;/strong> These weapons are underwhelming. Barely better than a non-magical item. You can sell them without a second thought.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>RP Tier:&lt;/strong> For those special weapons that just don’t work. Don’t use these weapons for any purpose other than role-playing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/a847bed635e7f60f097998bf37a97c0273fae9ff-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Absolute’s Warboard_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="absolutes-warboard---b-tier">Absolute&amp;rsquo;s Warboard - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Shield&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Word of the Absolute: This is an activatable ability that refreshes on a short rest. All unbranded targets in the area of effect receive the Bane condition for two turns. There is no saving throw to resist and this ability.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Patch 7 nerfed this item into oblivion. Before this patch I was saying it was the strongest item in the game, and now I struggle to get any value out of it at all. I am provisionally ranking it as a B-tier until I can better test the Word of the Absolute, because it isn&amp;rsquo;t functioning the way it used to.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/d939cd2a4fde106ab7d257025162bc2f2d32f7a3-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Adamantine Longsword_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="adamantine-longsword---b-tier">Adamantine Longsword - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Longsword&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Versatile Hitter: Hits with this weapon send the target reeling for one turn if it is used with one hand and two turns if it is used with two.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: there is no saving throw to resist the reeling condition. A reeling target has a -1 penalty to attack roles.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All of the Adamantine weapons are identical in effect, so I will use the same review for all of them. Reeling is fine. It&amp;rsquo;s just fine. You can count on this weapon, I just prefer my weapons to do damage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/abac72db573dc379a21e6a7ee9d7899af81a3de2-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Adamantine Mace_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="adamantine-mace---b-tier">Adamantine Mace - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Mace&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Swift Hitter: Hits with this weapon send the target reeling for one turn.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: there is no saving throw to resist the reeling condition. A reeling target has a -1 penalty to attack roles.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All of the Adamantine weapons are identical in effect, so I will use the same review for all of them. Reeling is fine. Its just fine. You can count on this weapon, I just prefer my weapons to do damage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/2d0498267dc9a9d4fb5898813a15193b536c68d5-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Adamantine Scimitar_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="adamantine-scimitar---b-tier">Adamantine Scimitar - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Scimitar&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Shift Hitter: Hits with this weapon send the target reeling for one turn.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: there is no saving throw to resist the reeling condition. A reeling target has a -1 penalty to attack roles.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All of the Adamantine weapons are identical in effect, so I will use the same review for all of them. Reeling is fine. Its just fine. You can count on this weapon, I just prefer my weapons to do damage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/83a729b4e2b46439b9d9f57999a8a1631287bced-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Blooded Greataxe_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="blooded-greataxe---b-tier">Blooded Greataxe - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Greataxe&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Relentless Revenge: When the wielder has 50% hit points or less, they deal an additional 1d6 slashing damage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This effect is honestly pretty good, since martials are incentivized by other items to flirt with the 50% HP line anyways. Greataxe’s also get the very fun Prepare weapon action. Its big issue is that heavy, two-handed weapons that do slashing damage are a stacked category, so this axe ends up way down the list.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/0b58c90ba442a5c3fb1094dbe003a4fb537bf04d-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Club_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="club-of-hill-giant-strength---b-tier">Club of Hill Giant Strength - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Club&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Splinter’s of a Giant’s Might: While wielding this weapon, the user’s strength is set to 15.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Its not good enough to be A-tier, but I use it on a lot of my runs. Its good to give to Wyll, since he only has a +1 modifier in both strength and dexterity. Mostly I just love the convenience of the carry weight boost on a weak party member!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/5b4ad7db32fdbaabbdc4646c71758c620a5bf96d-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Corellon’s Grace_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="corellons-grace---a-tier">Corellon&amp;rsquo;s Grace - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Staff&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unhampered Resistance: If the user of this staff takes damage while they are not wearing armor (robes are ok), they gain a 1d4 bonus to saving throws for two turns.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: The tooltip says “if they get attack while not wearing armor…” but this is incorrect. Right now, as I say above, the effect procs whenever they take damage while not wearing armor. That means it will proc when they get hit by an attack. It also means it will proc if they take damage from something that isn’t an attack, for example, a spell, or a ground effect.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is for your backline magic user to hold. The effect stacks with Bless, giving you, on average, a +5 to your saving throws. That is obviously amazing, but you have to risk losing your saving throw to get it. I prefer to just hide and not risk getting hit while I am concentrating and use a weapon that gives me a more proactive ability. Nevertheless, I can’t deny that this weapon is good.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/8f2eb860f5f89cb4b98b49ed1a299a2d25135cf6-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Deep Delver_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="deep-delver---b-tier">Deep Delver - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Warpick&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Dig Deep: Inflicts a condition on hit which lasts for three rounds, no save. Hits with the Deep Delver against targets with the condition deal an additional 1d4 piercing damage&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is a very underwhelming item by the time you get it. It gives a little more damage on consecutive hits. Just pass. If you want to use a warpick, go for a generic +1 version.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/83a729b4e2b46439b9d9f57999a8a1631287bced-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Doom Axe_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="doom-axe---c-tier">Doom Axe - C Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Greataxe&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Edge of Terror: Hits inflict a status condition that prevent the target from regaining hit points for two turns. Undead targets also have disadvantage on their attacks for the duration.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is offering an effect you can already get from a cantrip. Pass.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/9fcb4d41bc7ab088c087cf63992ca7c4fb036827-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Dragon’s Grasp_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="dragons-grasp---c-tier">Dragon&amp;rsquo;s Grasp - C Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Handaxe&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Burned Alive: Deals an additional 1d4 slashing damage to burning targets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Its low damage and very situational, so not worth more words than this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/199042f86630a4701dc0c860aa2503fc619caf8b-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Everburn_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="everburn-blade---a-tier">Everburn Blade - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Greatsword&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ever-Burning: An arcane flame that cannot be quenched; deals an extra 1d4 fire damage on hit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It’s a consistent and high damage heavy weapon that you can get early. Unlike others I’ve met on BG3 forums, I don’t consider it the best two-handed weapon in the game, or even the third best. Its still good though.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/83a729b4e2b46439b9d9f57999a8a1631287bced-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Exterminator’s Axe_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="exterminators-axe---b-tier">Exterminator&amp;rsquo;s Axe - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Greataxe&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Scourge of Pests: Deals an additional 1d6 fire damage to plants, insects, and small creatures.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A situational version of Blooded Greataxe. Not much to say here, its worth it if you are fighting the creatures its good against, otherwise its just a greataxe. I typically just sell this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/26864fe2c5064444c19a44e79aff68a43f77dce4-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Faithbreaker_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="faithbreaker---s-tier">Faithbreaker - S Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Warhammer&lt;/p>
&lt;p>+1 Enchantment&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Absolute Power: You make a special attack which deals an additional 1d6 force damage and pushes the target back 5m on a hit. You can use this attack once per short rest.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: Unlike the Battlemaster Maneuver Pushing Attack, there is no saving throw to resist the pushing effect on Absolute Power. You can also use this ability to push targets that otherwise couldn’t be pushed with shove, because they are too heavy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pushing targets can easily add guaranteed double digit damage in BG3, either from fall damage or from pushing into Cloud of Daggers. Faithbreaker offers the best push in the game. Not only can it push heavy creatures, it does it without a saving throw, all you need to do is hit the attack. This is the best one-handed weapon in the game in my opinion.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/5fe0655d97f51f914565ed680470fd3f3b45d592-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Firestoker_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="firestoker---c-tier">Firestoker - C Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Hand Crossbow&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Burned Alive: Deals an additional 1d4 slashing damage to burning targets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s the crossbow version of Dragon’s Grasp that you get much later on your runs. Completely underwhelming.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/a859181d67b18bd177c097d0c01f5df14d7a38e7-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Giant Breaker_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="giantbreaker---b-tier">Giantbreaker - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Heavy Crossbow&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Heavy Hitter: Hits with this weapon send the target reeling for two turns.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: there is no saving throw to resist the reeling condition. A reeling target has a -1 penalty to attack roles.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Reeling is fine. Its just fine. You can count on this weapon. It’s one of the better ranged weapons probably. I just prefer my weapons to do damage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/260287cc8a1875ce02ff6328eb43a3fa567df5f7-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Gith Corssbow_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="githyanki-crossbow---b-tier">Githyanki Crossbow - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Heavy Crossbow&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Psychic Vengeance: When the user is below 50% health, hits with this weapon deal an extra 1d4 psychic damage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some people report that, despite what the tooltip says, some Gith weapons do more damage than others. In all my tests, every Gith weapon functions the same. So I copy and past this review for each.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It’s a small boost to damage that is situational. However, psychic damage is seldom resisted, and dropping below 50% is fairly common, since other items also incentivize it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/628e932bcca93e6ed54959593a1fcc8a23497827-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Gith Greatsword_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="githyanki-greatsword---b-tier">Githyanki Greatsword - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Greatsword&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Psychic Vengeance: When the user is below 50% health, hits with this weapon deal an extra 1d4 psychic damage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some people report that, despite what the tooltip says, some Gith weapons do more damage than others. In all my tests, every Gith weapon functions the same. So I copy and past this review for each.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It’s a small boost to damage that is situational. However, psychic damage is seldom resisted, and dropping below 50% is fairly common, since other items also incentivize it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/d63bc702dded73c26ce01736d72a3070ea24963e-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Gith Longsword_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="githyanki-longsword---b-tier">Githyanki Longsword - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Longsword&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Psychic Vengeance: When the user is below 50% health, hits with this weapon deal an extra 1d4 psychic damage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some people report that, despite what the tooltip says, some Gith weapons do more damage than others. In all my tests, every Gith weapon functions the same. So I copy and past this review for each.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It’s a small boost to damage that is situational. However, psychic damage is seldom resisted, and dropping below 50% is fairly common, since other items also incentivize it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/9aaa247ecff9254ea0f2e93b7ef9932086821915-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Gith Shortsword_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="githyanki-shortsword---b-tier">Githyanki Shortsword - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Shortsword&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Psychic Vengeance: When the user is below 50% health, hits with this weapon deal an extra 1d4 psychic damage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some people report that, despite what the tooltip says, some Gith weapons do more damage than others. In all my tests, every Gith weapon functions the same. So I copy and past this review for each.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It’s a small boost to damage that is situational. However, psychic damage is seldom resisted, and dropping below 50% is fairly common, since other items also incentivize it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/a3b9c1572dcf0007933b8bbf1cd810b76da88bc2-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Glowing Shield_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="glowing-shield---b-tier">Glowing Shield - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Shield&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Loving Protection: Once per short rest, if you are below 50% Hit Points and take damage, you gain 8 temporary hit points.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It’s 8 temporary hit points per short rest, which adds up to 24 per long rest if you maximize it. It is boring, but not insignificant.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/7ef818ae7aee0e168d5e94168ee9d0d1e1124b25-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Intransigent Warhammer_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="intransigent-warhammer---a-tier">Intransigent Warhammer - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Warhammer&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Impulse Blast: Knocks nearby enemies prone after killing a target or getting a critical hit&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: I missed this item on my last run, so I haven’t tested it this patch. I’m going off memory here, but I believe it knocks targets back as well as down.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Knock back effects are often useful. You can force the proc with any auto crit mechanic, meaning you can control when you want to get this effect to some extent.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/e339ecd221e876e6905183389adbd85b86560fb5-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Jagged Spear_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="jagged-spear---a-tier">Jagged Spear - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Spear&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Torturer’s Edge: Hits with this weapon impose the tortured status condition. A tortured target has disadvantage on constitution saving throws.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: the status condition procs on 100% of hits, there is no saving throw.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is an enabling weapon, not a DPR weapon. There are some good spells that target constitution (ex: Thunderwave, Ray of Enfeeblement, Shatter, Moonbeam, etc). The fact that there is no save to resist the disadvantage really puts it over into A-tier. Put this on a character who is tanky but isn’t a striker (like Shadowheart, for example).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/1fa2e3ecdbae2297b28b7a539cf6ec845d7ddafb-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Light of Creation_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="light-of-creation---a-tier">Light of Creation - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Halberd&lt;/p>
&lt;p>+1 Enchantment&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unnamed: Deals an additional 1d6 lightening damage on hit but has a chance to stun the wielder for one turn if they are not a construct.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: This weapon stuns the wielder on about 20% of hits. However, what many people seem not to know is that you don’t actually lose a full turn from the stun. It prevents you from taking any more actions on your current turn, but the stun ends on the beginning of your next turn, allowing you to act normally. So, you lose whatever actions you had remaining on the turn you get stunned, and enemies have advantage on melee attacks against you until your next turn.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I love this weapon! It just does so much damage. It’s the highest, unconditional DPR weapon in the game so far, and that isn’t even factoring in that it does lightning damage, which you can double with Create Water. Assuming a base 75% chance to hit and a 16 strength, this weapon will average 13.83 damage per attack against a wet target, or 21.13 with Great Weapon Master!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/7fae0c9cfc67252f714fc8783f8d20658582a94b-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Loviatar’s Scourge_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="loviatars-scourge---c-tier">Loviatar&amp;rsquo;s Scourge - C Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Mace&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Willing Whip: Grants resistance to necrotic damage. Deals an additional 1d6 necrotic damage to nearby targets, including the wielder.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: This item is currently bugged, so that it does not deal the additional necrotic damage as the tooltip says.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Because its bugged, this only give you resistance to necrotic damage, which isn’t very common, so C-tier.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/39435565fdcaee67e8902dc7e2ba9bcdb4cb839d-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Nature’s Snare_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="natures-snare---b-tier">Nature&amp;rsquo;s Snare - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Staff&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Fly Trap: There is a chance to ensnare the target. Plant and beast creatures are immune.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: I’m not sure exactly how often the target is ensnared, but my experience is about 20% of attacks. Notice that I said “attacks” not “hits.” Fly Trap will proc even if your attack misses. When it procs the target is automatically ensnared without a saving throw. On subsequent turns, they will make a strength saving throw to break free. The DC is 10 + Int Mod or 10 + Spell Attribute Mod if you are a caster class (you should be if you use this weapon). The ensnared condition procs damage on the first turn they are ensnared as well as on every subsequent turn before they roll their saving throw (so there are at least 2 guaranteed procs).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Assuming I am right about the 20% proc rate, this feature adds around 1 damage per attack, which isn’t shabby as a feature, but on a quarterstaff its not going to add up to good DPR. You also can’t rely on the entangle procing when you need it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/2e202c898d42fe50a1d97a94f17c19e88eaffe87-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Paleoak_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="paleoak---b-tier">Paleoak - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Staff&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Faithwarden’s Vines: Allows you to cast Entangle as a lvl 1 spell once per long rest.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Faithwarden’t Stride: The wielder of this weapon is immune to all effects of the Entangle spell.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is situationally good on Druid, basically allowing you to make attacks with advantage. It may deserve A-tier, but I am just not a fan of Entangle. If you like Entangle and use it often, then consider this A-tier.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/b88f4c06d4ce1fb60adf14f0e19c46d78455585d-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Raindancer_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="raindancer---a-tier">Raindancer - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Staff&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Create Water: May cast Create Water as a lvl 1 spell once per short rest.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unlike Entangle, Create Water is an S-tier spell, and with this item it refreshes on a short rest! Fantastic way to guarantee Create Water casts on solo Wizard runs. Just a fantastic staff in general. I prefer to get this over Corellon’s Grace in the early game, although I do eventually swap it out for the Staff of Arcane Blessing later. Even after swapping it out, I keep this around as a side arm.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/6c1607e15d2c6abcdb12f57dce2b53fb5928fe38-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Ritual Axe_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="ritual-axe---b-tier">Ritual Axe - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Handaxe&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Scourge Mistress’ Bane: If you deal damage with this weapon, your target receives a 1d4 penalty to attack roles and saving throws for two turns.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: This does not stack with the Bane spell. There is no saving throw to resist.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bane is a potent debuff, as we have discussed. However, there are already several ways to proc Bane, even on hit (Absolute’s Warboard, Gloves of Power). Because of that, I find I that I rarely use Ritual Axe. If you aren’t using any other Bane item, Ritual Axe could be considered A-tier.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/4df929b0ebbe157501b1a08d8fcc6196a90ea542-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Ritual Dagger_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="ritual-dagger---b-tier">Ritual Dagger - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Dagger&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Blood Sacrifice: As a bonus action, you can deal 1d4 slashing damage to yourself in order to gain a 1d4 bonus to attack roles and saving throws for one round.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Pain Maiden’s Blessing: If you deal damage with this weapon you receive a 1d4 bonus to attack roles and saving throws for one round.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: the effects do not stack with Bless. However, they also do not require concentration.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Similar to Ritual Axe, there are already better ways of getting Bless than to expend a valuable weapon slot.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/4653c7aac597e977d8ff6bf5976979619a79dd6b-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Shattered Flail_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="shattered-flail---a-tier">Shattered Flail - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Mace&lt;/p>
&lt;p>+2 Enchantment&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Yeenoghu’s Gift: Dealing damage with this weapon heals the user 1d6 hp and instills them with an insatiable hunger – they can go mad if they do not deal damage each turn.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: In all the times I’ve used Shattered Flail I have never had a character go mad.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is another one of my favorite weapons! It’s the only +2 weapon in the game and it heals on hit as well. If you add up its healing with its damage it averages 5.5 damage swing per hit, which is a lot. For this reason, I like to use it in builds that make lots of attacks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/aae4893bad957c3b8d573e2add7643ab1e2df3a1-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="SS of First Blood_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="shortsword-of-first-blood---a-tier">Shortsword of First Blood - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Shortsword&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Break the Unbroken: Deals an additional 1d8 damage if the target is full health.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The value of this really depends on your play style I suppose. It could be either B or A, depending on how you spread out your damage. There isn’t much to explain, it does a lot of damage on first hits. I find that it is good as a main hand weapon for Rogues.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/e0512777fd3eaffbddbabaf3e8ed720d31bf68d6-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Sickle of Booal_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="sickle-of-booal---rp-tier">Sickle of Booal - RP Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Sickle&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Booal’s Benediction: Give the wielder advantage when attacking bleeding targets.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: Everyone says it gives you advantage when attacking bleeding victims, but haven’t been able to replicate that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This weapon is bugged right now, making it useless. I expect it would be B-tier,&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/545b06506a04f374f545d2b8ad11958e62bad59a-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Light Hammer &amp;#43;1_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="skybreaker---b-tier">Skybreaker - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Light Hammer&lt;/p>
&lt;p>+1 Enchantment&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Searing Smite: Allows you to use the spell Searing Smite (at 1st level) once per long rest.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Searing Smite is a C-tier spell at best, and that’s practically all this item offers. The +1 enchantment is enough to keep it out of C-tier itself though.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/e426f29e45bcb21011a2e78c4f228f3557f2e032-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Spellthief_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="spellthief---s-tier">Spellthief - S Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Longbow&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Arcane Vehemence: Once per Short Rest, you regain a 1st level Spell Slot when you land a critical hit with the Spellthief.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: If you crit with a spell or cantrip while wielding Spellthief you still get a spell slot returned.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Spells are incredible, and this bow gives you an extra one per short rest (three per long rest). Its easy to guarantee crits in BG3 with Sleep, Tasha’s, Hold Person, etc. If you plan carefully, you can swap this item around to all your spellcasters, making sure each of them get the bonus spells. You don’t need to be proficient in Longbows to use it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/591e43714ba1a24d25d63f2a2356bd4b40a0d7e6-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Sorrow_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="sorrow---b-tier">Sorrow - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Glaive&lt;/p>
&lt;p>+1 Enchantment&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ensnaring Strike: Allows you to use Ensnaring Strike as a level 1 spell once per short rest.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Regret: The user takes 1 psychic damage whenever they deal damage with this weapon.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This weapon needs a buff in my opinion. The look and the way you get it are so cool, but then it just sucks as a weapon. Its not even the 1 psychic damage that ruins it, its Ensnaring Strike. Its just not a good spell… I’m not sure how to fix it, may make it +2? I also wish basic enchantments would effect the DC of weapon action and spells, that might help.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/811d468b8a0419689ea4d383be634d034744baed-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Staff of Arcane Blessing_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="staff-of-arcane-blessing---s-tier">Staff of Arcane Blessing - S Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Staff&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Bless: Allows you to cast Bless as a level 1 spell once per long rest.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mystra’s Blessing: When you cast Bless while wielding this staff you gain an additional 1d4 bonus to attack roles and saving throws. This bonus increases to an additional 2d4 for spell attacks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: This spell does not do what it says it does. The only effect it gives is a +1d4 (2d4 total) to spell attacks. You do not get any bonuses to normal attack roles and saving throws.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Even though it is only a fraction as good as the tooltip says it should be, its still soooo good. This turns spells like Flame Blade and Scorching Ray into killers. You should be spamming Bless anyways, so any boost to Bless is going to add up to a big bonus just from the frequency of the cast.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/949aebb8574926c79e51dbcd1a561f06b7229754-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Staff of Crones_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="staff-of-crones---rp-tier">Staff of Crones - RP Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Staff&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Ray of Sickness: While wielding this staff, you can cast Ray of Sickness without expending a spell slot. When you do this you simultaneously target yourself with the same spell.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If Ray of Sickness didn’t hit you as well as your enemy this would be A-tier, effectively giving you a boosted cantrip. As it is right now, its just not worth using. Feed it to Gale.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/9f6911e0c75929ca9a762530a8ce45880f7c6896-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Sussur Dagger_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="sussur-dagger---a-tier">Sussur Dagger - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Dagger&lt;/p>
&lt;p>+1 Enchantment&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Silence the Enemy: Silences the target for one turn on hit. There is no save, and it procs on every hit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All of the Sussur weapons are identical in effect, so I will use the same review for all of them. A single target silence that sticks to an enemy is actually better than the AoE Silence spell, because they can’t walk out of a status condition. As I have already said, spell are powerful, so stopping spells from being cast is very valuable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/6862680eacb196dd62ea419d42b179866c75aa3d-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Sussur Greatsword_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="sussur-greatsword---a-tier">Sussur Greatsword - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Greatsword&lt;/p>
&lt;p>+1 Enchantment&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Silence the Enemy: Silences the target on hit. There is no save, and it procs on every hit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All of the Sussur weapons are identical in effect, so I will use the same review for all of them. A single target silence that sticks to an enemy is actually better than the AoE Silence spell, because they can’t walk out of a status condition. As I have already said, spell are powerful, so stopping spells from being cast is very valuable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/463a1529ed91ce313f260f9f5e38b16302b3747d-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Sussur Sickle_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="sussur-sickle---a-tier">Sussur Sickle - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Sickle&lt;/p>
&lt;p>+1 Enchantment&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Silence the Enemy: Silences the target on hit. There is no save, and it procs on every hit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All of the Sussur weapons are identical in effect, so I will use the same review for all of them. A single target silence that sticks to an enemy is actually better than the AoE Silence spell, because they can’t walk out of a status condition. As I have already said, spell are powerful, so stopping spells from being cast is very valuable.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/bb67bf44a2ab0460d0fc9a9d8d9494374ded1393-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Sword of Justice_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="sword-of-justice---s-tier">Sword of Justice - S Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Greatsword&lt;/p>
&lt;p>+1 Enchantment&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tyr’s Protection: Allows you to cast Shield of Faith on yourself as a bonus action.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I couldn’t find a png image for this one, so I used a generic greatsword instead. I consider this to be the best two-handed weapon in the game. It allows for an efficient use of you concentration slot, which many two-handed weapon users don’t have. The extra AC also helps proc Ripostes for Battlemasters. All around an awesome weapon that you can get very early in the game.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/c0a66f98f2fafffb27fc0daa18ac77821cb9fb9d-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Sword of Screams_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="sword-of-screams---a-tier">Sword of Screams - A Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Rapier&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Screams: Deals an additional 1d4 psychic damage on hit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s a rapier that will deal an additional 2.5 damage on hit. Like the finesse weapon version of Everburn, only you get it much, much later. Technically it&amp;rsquo;s the highest, one-handed pure damage per hit in the game with no asterisk. I’ve rated it an A-tier, but I think it is still worse than the mainstays of one-handed weapons: Shattered Flail and Faithbreaker.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/93b6fcc105170b4d9915506baf823d52636974a8-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="The Wartcher’s Guide_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-watchers-guide---b-tier">The Watcher&amp;rsquo;s Guide - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Spear&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Death’s Promise: When the spear misses its target, the wielder&amp;rsquo;s next attack against that target is made with advantage.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What’s there to say about this? Its helps you hit more often. There aren’t any tricks for it that I know of. You used to be able to get Death’s Promise on your cantrips by holding The Watcher’s Guide while casting them, but it hasn’t worked for me for a while (it was fixed on Patch 5, my thanks to reddit user Certain_Childhood849 for bringing this to my attention). It could be used to help proc Sneak Attacks, except that it isn’t a finesse weapon, so it can’t. Its just a mediocre weapon, no tricks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/2d828f238bfa98bf0eedfab90ac00a13d2e97cc7-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Vision of the Absolute_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="vision-of-the-absolute---b-tier">Vision of the Absolute - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Spear&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Absolute Night: There is a chance that you will blind your target for two rounds on hit. Deals an additional 2d6 piercing damage to certain targets that sport multiple eyes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: In my tests, I proc blind on around 40% of hits, not attacks. You need to hit to proc the blind. When it procs, there is no saving throw and lasts for two rounds with no saving throw. It does extra damage to spiders and spectators (my thanks to reddit user TrustKind for the correction on spiders).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is one of the better B-tiers in my opinion, and you can get it early. Keep it around for fights against spectators or spiders.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/a161d0c7f6506f0a7568d4f2c3ad246cbe86a822-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Worgfang_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="worgfang---c-tier">Worgfang - C Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Dagger&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Goblin’s Undoing: Goblins had disadvantage on attacks against the wielder of this weapon.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Its decent for clearing the goblin camp, if you prioritize getting it before then. I usually don’t, because I just don’t care about it enough.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/si39ve47/production/7fae0c9cfc67252f714fc8783f8d20658582a94b-150x150.png?w=150&amp;amp;auto=format"
loading="lazy"
alt="Xyanyde_BG3"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="xyanyde---b-tier">Xyanyde - B Tier
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Weapon Type: Mace&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Xyanyde’s Fire: Chance to encase its target in a sinister Faerie Fire, granting advantage on Attack Rolls against the target.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note: Faerie Fire procs on about 20% of attacks. It can proc on misses.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How do you pronounce this name? Is is “Zy-un-ide,” like the word cyanide? That sounds wrong… Maybe “Zy-un-eye-day?” also sounds dumb. I prefer to just change the pronunciation of the second “y’ and pronounce it “Zy-an-ee-day.” Whichever way you prefer, this weapon just isn’t that good. For a debuffing weapon, its better to go with the Jagged Spear.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="unique-weapons-final-rankings">Unique Weapons Final Rankings
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>&lt;strong>S Tier:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Faithbreaker, Spellthief, Staff of Arcane Blessing, Sword of Justice&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>A Tier:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Corellon’s Grace, Everburn, Intransigent Warhammer, Jagged Spear, Light of Creation, Rain Dancer, Shattered Flail, Short Sword of First Blood, Sussur Weapons, Sword of Screams.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>B Tier:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Absolute&amp;rsquo;s Warboard, Adamantine Weapons, Blooded Greataxe, Club of Hill Giant Strength, Deep Delver, Exterminator’s Axe, Giantbreaker, Gith Weapons, Glowing Shield, Light Hammer +1, Nature’s Snare, Pale Oak, Ritual Axe, Ritual Dagger, Sorrow, The Watcher’s Guide, Visions of the Absolute, Xyanyde&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>C Tier:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Doom Axe, Dragon’s Grasp, Firestoker, Loviatar’s Scourge, Worgfang,&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>RP Tier:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sickle of Booal, Staff of Crones&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here is a &lt;a class="link" href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1hEptz8WN_auHCxcLfd0XDAd7cfV0Az7T/edit?usp=sharing&amp;amp;ouid=102922927028635040581&amp;amp;rtpof=true&amp;amp;sd=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>helpful spreadsheet&lt;/a> I made for myself that charts relative damage per attack of the weapons you would pick for their damage.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Thanks for reading!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you want to discuss this article with me or others, you can do so &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AestusGuides/comments/std2v6/bg3_weapon_tier_list/?utm_source=share&amp;amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;amp;context=3" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>here&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This article has actually been available for early access for over two weeks on my brand new Patreon! I put a lot of time into these articles, and I have plans to write many more. If you want to enable that please consider supporting me through Patreon. There are several tiers which will give you access to loads of exclusive and early access content! You can find my page &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.patreon.com/user?u=52365991&amp;amp;fan_landing=true" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.aestusguides.com/articles" >Return home&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>